<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Mango Ice Cream]]></title>
  <link href="http://kevinpan.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kevinpan.me/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-18T00:35:49-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://kevinpan.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kevin Pan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[11pm Ponderings of an Overworking Intern]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/03/17/we-live-in-an-autocratic-world/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-17T23:25:47-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/03/17/we-live-in-an-autocratic-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m sitting here in Twitch.tv’s video broadcast lab at 11:26pm on a Thursday night because Intel’s Quick Sync encoder quietly inserts one extra frame to a 500 frame video if you specify the input video’s framerate at 50. This messes up all the objective video metrics leaving me completely perplexed for the majority of the evening.</p>

<p>The lab’s empty, most of the office is probably empty, and here I am, one solitary intern who should reallly reallly reallllyy go home soon. It’s times like these when you become a philosopher. This phenomenon is akin to that which occurs often in long showers and evening bus rides. The mind wanders and simultaneously ponders the world.</p>

<p>The topic of reflection for tonight was social structures, in particular, systems of government. Democracy vs autocracy. What a classic. I spent most of my life in “Western” societies and I am no stranger to the benevolence of democracy and the dangers of autocracy. It is an undeniable fact that a democractic government is one that poses the least risks for the governed. We cherish our democratic values here and we wear them proudly.</p>

<p>It was then that I realized how contradictory our everyday lives were to democracy. I’ve never considered this but one of the largest institutions in our lives, at least for the majority of us, is almost entirely nondemocratic. The institution I’m referring to, of course, is the company. 5 days a week we go to work, listen to what our managers want us to do, and do it. By design, the majority of employees often have very little say in the overall direction of the company.</p>

<p>So in short, we spend most of our adult lives being part of autocratic machines and every few years we go to the polls and vote… Why am I still in the office?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Santa Cruz-ing down Carillo Highway (Part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/03/14/santa-cruz-ing-down-highway-1-and-how-i-discovered-my-limits/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-14T23:20:14-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/03/14/santa-cruz-ing-down-highway-1-and-how-i-discovered-my-limits</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Michelle and I decided to bike to Santa Cruz on President’s Day Weekend. The distance from San Francisco to Santa Cruz, if you stick to the west coast down Cabrillo Highway, is about 130km, or 80 miles for the imperially inclined. I’ve biked relatively long distances before in a day but never this long. In my last internship in the Bay Area, I had biked from Palo Alto to San Francisco downtown which is about 60km and there was another bike trip this term up north in Marin County where I biked for a bit more than 60km. Maybe it was 70, I don’t remember. In any case, for experienced bikers, this is not too bad but for a fledgling one like myself, this is a significant undertaking.</p>

<div style="text-align: center"><img style="width: 60%; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="http://imgur.com/RQd0aYO.jpg" /></div>

<p>My bike is a used 2015 Raleigh Revenio 1.0, the most beginner of beginner road bikes. However, compared to the old hybrid bike I was using last work term, a road bike is a tremendous improvement. I really like the colour scheme it has going for it too. White handle bars, white tires, and a silvery-white frame that has drawn praise where praise is not deserved. Yes, to the inexperienced observer, this bike was definitely not crappy (not that I would call my bike crappy, even though it’s not something to write home about). Michelle’s bike, on the other hand, is a really nice and new Specialized Dolce.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The biggest mistake I made before this trip was ever commiting to the 130km in one day, specifically because I had nowhere near enough sleep for me to push through.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The biggest mistake I made before this trip was ever commiting to the 130km in one day, specifically because I had nowhere near enough sleep for me to push through. I had a bout of insomnia a couple days before the trip for whatever reason. I wasn’t nervous, I ate well, I exercised, and yet my mind ran circles around me when it was time to sleep. As such, I slept a grand total of 2 hours the night before the big trip. Yes, 2 hours. Not 4, not 3, but 2. The last time I did this I was mercilessly butchered by a Stats exam (and no, it was not because I wasn’t prepared, or so I would like to think). In any case, people that know me know that I need sleep. I can hardly survive on 6 hours or less of sleep and that is without hours on end of rigorous biking. 2 hours of sleep and 130km of biking made for an insurmountable goal.</p>

<p>Hindsight is 20/20 and I mistakenly commit to this goal. Was I worried? Yes. Was I foolish? Doubly so. But where’s the fun in life without the risks? So I woke up at 6 in the morning feeling like a zombie fresh out of a coffin, cleaned myself up, picked up my packed gear, and headed out to meet Michelle. Our plan was to stay in Santa Cruz for a couple nights before biking back on Monday.</p>

<p>The first few kilometres as we cut through the city were quite tiring honestly. I’ve never biked with this much weight on my back. Two full water bottles, a bike lock, a change of clothes, and energy bars made for a sore back. The iota of sleep I had the night before didn’t help either. Most bikers distribute this weight on little pouches around the bike which not only keeps the centre of gravity low, but also puts less strain on the body and more so on the legs. Me, being a complete newbie to long distance biking, had a backpack.</p>

<p>It was quite surprising to me, after around 15 km of biking when we reached Skyline Drive, that my mind and body seemingly did a complete 360 and I felt like I had all the energy in the world. Perhaps it’s the cardio I’ve been doing for so long, or perhaps it’s the delicious McDonald’s™ Sausage McMuffin with Egg sandwich I devoured for breakfast. In any case, the sore back, the all around tiredness from before, it was all gone once we reached this quiet, quaint neighbourhood road that was right by the coast. Unfortunately, most of the ocean view was blocked by the houses lining the west side of the road.</p>

<p><img align="left" style="width: 50%; margin-right: 10px;" src="http://imgur.com/1xzayV6.jpg" /></p>

<p>All this changed when we hit a right and turned onto Palmetto Avenue. Right there in front of us was the Pacific coast, blue ocean that stretched across the horizon, the faint smell of salt in the gentle breeze, and the soft rumble of distant waves crashing against the shore. This ride was going to be breathtaking, and this was just a preview for what lay ahead.</p>

<div style="clear: both"></div>

<hr />

<p>The first significant landmark was the Pacifica State Beach of which the following BEAUTIFUL and ARTISTIC photo was taken (Michelle doesn’t think so but she’s wrong ;)). We continued hugging the coast, riding south for a few kilometres before veering off to the right on Crespi Drive to head for the mountains. Yes. That’s right, mountains, because apparently this is much more preferred than biking down the next stretch of highway.</p>

<div style="text-align: center"><img style="width: 80%; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="http://imgur.com/wPGO3qd.jpg" /></div>

<p>In any case, the mountain road was quite steep, we needed to climb around 300 metres of elevation in 3-4 kilometers. The road was poorly maintained, although we did see quite a few bikers on road bikes climbing with us. And here lies the third mistake. I have never learned the proper form to climbing whilst biking and I think I unnecessarily expanded a large amount of energy going up. I mean, I felt great but we still had around a 100km more to bike for the rest of the day, and definitely many more climbs. It was naïve of me to spend any significant amount of energy here.</p>

<p>The road down the mountain was even worse than the way up. It was basically a glorified stretch of dirt and rocks. Definitely not road bike territory. There were tons of holes and ridges in the path that made for a jarring ride down. At least the view was nice. We could see the ocean again.</p>

<p><img align="right" style="width: 50%; margin-left: 10px" src="http://imgur.com/Djpbh3A.jpg" /></p>

<p>It was going down this mountain road that I had the first fall I can ever remember in a long while. And it was terrible. There was this ridge in the dirt path that my front tire slid on and I careened off the bike. My left elbow and knees suffered pretty large scrapes, especially my elbow. It was a mess of torn skin, tissue, blood, and dirt. Man, why didn’t I bring any sort of first aid supplies on this trip. THANKFULLY, Michelle, being the ever cautious, ever wise friend, had polysporin. I was quite worried about a terrible infection since the next pharmacy was miles south in Half Moon Bay. This is me here with a poorly washed wound and makeshift gauze that comprised of my spare boxers and a rubber hair band. Marvelous.</p>

<p>This fall hit my drive hard. By the time we reached Half Moon Bay, the 2 hours of sleep really started to get to me. I had a hard time keeping my eyes open in the blazing noon sun. I really just wanted to turn that flaming ball of hydrogen off. Half Moon Bay, despite it’s name, was NOT the halfway point to Santa Cruz. There was still a whopping 80km to our destination. 80 KILOMETRES and I’m already in this state. Kevin, why didn’t you just stop?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Half Moon Bay, despite it’s name, was NOT the halfway point to Santa Cruz. There was still a whopping 80km to our destination. 80 KILOMETRES and I’m already in this state. Kevin, why didn’t you just stop?</p>
</blockquote>

<div style="text-align: center"><img style="width: 80%; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="http://imgur.com/2dLCHBR.jpg" /></div>

<p>We stopped by a plaza to get some first aid and food. At this point, I was really starting to feel the drowsiness. Could I make it? Could I ride another 80km? Perhaps it was because of this sad state that I couldn’t make a rational decision. We were only 50km into the bike ride! How could we stop now? Little did I know the next motel past Half Moon Bay was miles, miles south. Kevin, why didn’t you check?</p>

<p>So I paddle and I paddle and the afternoon sun kept beating down on me and I kept fighting off the doubt. At one point in time, I started closing my eyes even as we biked down the relatively busy highway. A little past Half Moon Bay were two pretty massive climbs, 150 metres of elevation each and it was here that I knew I couldn’t go any further. Poor climbing form, an intense drowsiness, and a badly injured elbow made for a potent combination. At one point, I remember having to stop at a rather large highway shoulder halfway up a climb to lie down and rest by the grass. The large shoulder was not a coincidence, the view of the Pacific coast here was incredible but all I wanted was a cozy bed and a roof above. At the top of the second climb, we decided to pump my bike tires of my bike since this really helps with the speed of the bike. What a disaster this was! The janky $20 portable bike pump I got online coughed and wheezed air into the tires and it was definitely a workout pumping that thing. At one point we completely deflated the back tire because a little rubbery ring came off the tip of the pump and we had no idea what it was for. So we foolishly attached the nozzle to the tire, the typical loud wheezing sound occurs but never subsides. As the gauge hand of the pump swung left at an ever accelerating rate, panic ensued. Luckily it was just a matter of pushing and proding the ring back into the pump nozzle. Anyways, I drained a large amount of what remained of my energy because of this pumping debacle and I was ready to call it quits.</p>

<p>We had no idea things were going to get much, much worse.</p>

<p>PS: I’m not sorry for the title pun ☺</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Great Free Speech Conundrum]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/03/13/the-great-free-speech-conundrum/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-13T16:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/03/13/the-great-free-speech-conundrum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Freedom of speech is generally defined as “the right to communicate one’s opinions and ideas without fear of government retaliation or censorship”. Sounds perfectly reasonable and perfectly necessary for a modern society. A government that allows it’s citizens to voice their opinions is a government that welcomes innovation, improvement, and very importantly, protects itself from corruption.</p>

<p>However, reality is infinitely more complex. The modern information age allows people that are tens of thousands of miles away to communicate as if they were right next to each other. Opinions and ideas can be spread to millions of people halfway across the globe in an instant. This obviously comes with a myriad of advantages for civilization at large. The quick distribution of ideas enables collaboration and innovation at a scale never before seen. BUT, it also allows for malicious entities to manipulate millions of people quickly and efficiently.</p>

<p>Before I continue, I would like to point out how powerful a unified, angry population is. Governments throughout the ages have been created and toppled by the will of the governed. Notable historical Western examples include the French and Russian revolutions where impoverished, passionate peasants tore down monarchies and executed the de facto rulers. More recent examples include the Arab Spring revolutions.</p>

<p>Now let’s shift perspectives. Humans are by nature competitive creatures and this trait is, if I dare say, amplified even further at the level of statehood. Most governments want the best for their population. A happy population makes for a successful government and one of the most direct ways to achieve this is through wealth. But wealth is not an infinite resource and when certain countries adopt foreign policies that directly affects another’s ability to grow in wealth, or stay wealthy, conflicts occur. In many cases, direct, open warfare follows. Fortunately, wars are risky, time consuming, and expensive.</p>

<p>A much more desirable option is to utilize the will of a government’s own people to change said government’s policies. The reasoning is crystal clear here. Why would you send your own citizens to fight wars when you could have the citizens of your enemies fight your wars for you?</p>

<p>But how does one government go about turning a significant group of a foreign country’s population against their own government? Ever heard of the term propaganda? Now let’s look at the internet and how incredibly easy it is to voice opinions and spread a message. Let’s be frank here, the internet is truly a perfect medium for propaganda dissemination. Foreign policy makers all over the world are not stupid; they understand the power of the internet and are actively using it to their advantage.</p>

<p>This is where the great free speech conundrum manifests itself. In an ideal world, a government would want its population to exercise free speech. What it does not want is to have foreign entities abuse local free speech policies to foster dissent and general social unrest. But how does one go about filtering out the “evil” speech from the “good” speech. When do you cross the line and start encroaching on the free speech rights of your own citizens? This is an incredibly hard problem that deserves more awareness and discussion than it receives today. I am of the opinion that people are quick to shun certain policies that have potential to violate free speech but is at the same time, necessary to protect the population from foreign, malevolent forces.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But how does one go about filtering out the “evil” speech from the “good” speech. When do you cross the line and start encroaching on the free speech rights of your own citizens? This is an incredibly hard problem that deserves more awareness and discussion than it receives today.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In any case, my main goal for this post is to hopefully get the reader thinking about this issue. As I’ve mentioned before, there is really no easy solution to the free speech conundrum (case in point, the NSA). However, I am hopeful that there is definitely a solution out there that correctly balances free speech and “internet protection” (sorry, I couldn’t think of a better term…) and the more dialogue there is on this issue, the faster we can reach a sensible compromise.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On growing up with anxiety...]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/03/12/on-growing-up-with-anxiety/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-12T02:48:25-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/03/12/on-growing-up-with-anxiety</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To be honest I’m not completely comfortable with writing this post. I guess it’s probably because I’m sharing something about myself that I’m not entirely proud of… sort of like a secret, personal weakness that I’m exposing to the reader. I’ve long been able to cope and even overcome, if I daresay, most of these issues but there is this mysterious mental health stigma that pervades society and is definitely affecting me as I write this. However, I’m quite sure that many people can relate to at least some of my experiences and I hope that by sharing my anxiety story, I can somehow, in some way, help those that are still silently struggling against their inner beast.</p>

<p>My story begins in my adolescent years… sometime during middle school when I had a terrible bout of OCD (Obsessive Compulsive Disorder). Like most cases of OCD, it starts out with really minor things like having a tendency to set the audio volume to certain numbers and [ …some other trivial example. I added the “and” for sentence flow and I can’t think of any examples right now]. Most people are like this right? Perfectly normal unless you have a particular sensitivity towards OCD. Unfortunately I did and the symptoms became more and more severe. At the worst stages, I exhibited most of the textbook symptoms of OCD like having elaborate, stressful, and terribly time consuming rituals that involved things like obsessive handwashing and ordering objects in my room (ordering as in making sure everything is in the perfect place, any object that’s even a tad bit off angle MUST be corrected at all costs).</p>

<p>So why did I act out all these “rituals”? At the core of the problem was anxiety. Most of the time I acted because I was scared that if I didn’t, something bad would happen. Maybe this is why there’s this stigma around mental health. It’s just weird, silly, hard to explain, and incredibly embarrassing. In any case, it’s embarrassing at my expense so please keep reading ;)</p>

<p>Also, as a side note, this is why these OCD rituals are so time consuming. If I didn’t do one correctly, I had a primal desire to restart. And restart I did. Many, many times.</p>

<p>One of the ABSOLUTE WORST things about having OCD as a child, at least for me, was that I didn’t understand this and I was scared and embarrassed to talk about it to anyone around me. It wasn’t my OCD symptoms that made it hard for me to share though, it was all the fears, the worrying thoughts that were driving me to act out on them. These thoughts were horrible and often times weird and irrational. So irrational that I don’t even want to talk about them now. Fortunately, I was able to grow out of OCD but I couldn’t free myself of these thoughts.</p>

<p>It is my understanding today that all these negative thoughts were the manifestation of my anxiety. This struggle with OCD was just a small battle in my overarching war against it.</p>

<p>Come high school, I was rid of OCD but anxiety was a monster that clung to me and struck time and time again. I’ve always thought of myself as a little slower to mature emotionally compared to my peers and this, combined with all the negative emotions from anxiety, made a potent combination that, at times, overwhelmed me. Needless to say, high school wasn’t easy.</p>

<p>Again, I kept everything to myself. It was the same story, anxiety created worries and fears that were too weird and embarrassing to share. If I couldn’t share the root cause of my frustration and depression, how could anyone else help?</p>

<p>So I soldiered on and come university, things turned for the better as I became more emotionally mature and as they say, “grew into myself”. But I still had anxiety and I still had these thoughts. They were not necessarily the same as the thoughts a year ago or even a couple months ago but they were just as embarrasing, just as irrational. Anxiety “attacks” were less frequent but not any bit less potent. At the height of any one attack, rational thought is completely and utterly overwhelmed by negative emotions. It sucks.</p>

<p>In any case, this is a HAPPY story and I did eventually overcome anxiety in a spectacular fashion. Word choice is important here, because I never really got rid of anxiety. It’s still a beast that continues today to affect me, albeit in a much more limited and tolerable fashion. I realised sometime around the start of my last school term that I’ve always tackled anxiety the wrong way. I alienated it, fought it, rejected it as a part of who I am. In other words, I couldn’t accept anxiety as being a part of me. But anxiety really is a part of me, and it is one of the many things that define who I am. This one thought, this one realization that I will never get rid of anxiety because it is a part of me made a profound change. Whenever I started obsessing over some stupid anxiety-driven thought, instead of fighting it, I accepted it. I embraced anxiety and stopped trying to control it. In return, my anxiety stopped controlling me. Magically, through acceptance, I stopped worrying.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I embraced anxiety and stopped trying to control it. In return, my anxiety stopped controlling me. Magically, through acceptance, I stopped worrying.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="a-final-note">A final note…</h2>

<p>I didn’t mention this before but a lot of my anxiety-driven fears have another common theme besides being weird and embarrassing, they were always about LOSS. Somehow, deep within me, there is a strong, primal fear for loss. And this is how acceptance really helped. Instead of fearing loss, I mentally accepted loss. This is really hard to put into words but basically, if I was going to lose something and was powerless to stop it, I will lose it and then this loss becomes a part of who I am. This whole time the one thing that is constant, the one solid thing that I can rely on, is that I am me and that will never change :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick Tips For a Healthier Lifestyle as a College Student]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2015/05/17/quick-tips-for-a-healthier-lifestyle-as-a-college-student/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-17T20:48:56-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2015/05/17/quick-tips-for-a-healthier-lifestyle-as-a-college-student</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m going to preface this post by saying that I even though I write as if I’m an authoritative figure on leading healthy lifestyles, I’m not. The things I mention here worked and is still working for me (at least that’s what I’m inclined to believe).</p>

<hr />

<p>For many of us, going to college means living away from home for the first time. There are many other firsts that come with moving out… you might have to start doing your own laundry for the first time, or start cooking your own dinners. As a third year university student, I’ve been through all these firsts and learned quite a few things along the way.</p>

<p>One of the best things about living away from home is the freedom. You get to do whatever you want now without having parents nosing around. But that also means the possibility of developing unhealthy lifestyle habits, especially dietary habits, that you might regret later on.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What people are not good at, though, is identifying what’s missing in their diet, mainly because people don’t typically think of these things.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Let me first focus on dietary habits. When it comes to your diet, it’s important to realize that it doesn’t necessarily have to be what you’re eating that makes it unhealthy, it could also be from what you’re NOT eating. I think everyone’s pretty good at identifying generally unhealthy foods (e.g. greasy, sugary, starchy, …) so I won’t elaborate on this. What people are not good at, though, is identifying what’s missing in their diet, mainly because people don’t typically think of these things. Back home, your parents made your food and you ate it. So my best diet advice for you is to keep in mind what nutrients you might have missed out on in your current diet. When I say nutrients I mean things like calcium, iron, vitamin B, and vitamin D.</p>

<p>An extra comment on diet. It’s always good to keep in mind there are some foods that are just so much more efficient than others at giving you the nutrients you need. For example, nuts and seeds are packed with protein, vitamins, and minerals. Find these foods, eat them regularly.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And you can’t fault people for this; exercise is painful. Cardio is hard on both the mind and the body, weight lifting is strenuous.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Besides a healthy diet, a healthy lifestyle also warrants that you stay physically active (I know, how generic, who doesn’t know this?). Truth is, people do know this but many people don’t act on it. And you can’t fault people for this; exercise is painful. Cardio is hard on both the mind and the body, weight lifting is strenuous. Okay, maybe weight lifting is an exception, since having bulging muscles is strong enough motivation to keep many guys going back to the gym. But cardio, in my experience, is something many people shy away from. Like I mentioned, it’s not easy. You’re often uncomfortable physically and bored out of your mind on that treadmill or elliptical. For me personally, I’ve made cardio, specifically running, a key part of my lifestyle. I’ve run enough times to not have to deal with the physical discomfort part but it’s still often quite boring.</p>

<p>But no worries, it doesn’t have to be this way. There’s another form of exercise I learned recently that, apparently, is significantly better than steady-state cardio. It’s called High Intensity Interval Training (HIIT). Most often applied to running, what it means is to break your running sessions into multiple sprinting and resting periods. For example, you would sprint 1 minute, rest 1 minute, and so forth. This type of exercise burns calories at a much faster rate than steady-state cardio and, as claimed by countless resources online, is just plain better. No matter the calorie burning rate, one thing that’s for sure is that HIIT is not boring. You’re constantly changing your pace so it’s not monotonous and segmenting your workout session into 1 or 2 minute increments make it go by a lot faster. This, to me, is one of the best things about HIIT.</p>

<p>Now that you have a wholesome diet and you’re in love with HIIT and exercising frequently, you must think that you’re all set for a healthy lifestyle right? Yes you are. Why are you still reading?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…a healthy lifestyle isn’t all about being physically healthy. You have to be mentally healthy too.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>No I’m kidding, a healthy lifestyle isn’t all about being physically healthy. You have to be mentally healthy too. What do I mean by this? Well, sometimes, instead of bingeing on TV shows like Game of Thrones or Breaking Bad or Suits, you might choose to read something that holds more weight… something where you will learn and not just learn for the sake of learning, but learn towards whatever goal you have. I guess the best advice I can give is to make sure you’re PASSIONATE about at least something in life and you’re actively working on improving that thing you’re passionate about. If you aren’t and you find yourself watching too many TV shows or movies or playing too many videos games or partying, maybe you should find that passion.</p>

<p>One of the most common advice I’ve heard from people much older, much wiser than I is to NOT WASTE TIME when you’re young. Time is precious and it might feel like you have a lot now, but it goes by exponentially as you age. And yes, you’ve heard this before, excuse me for being so cliché, but many people simply don’t do anything about it. Don’t be like “many people”, lead a purposeful life.</p>

<p>A middle-aged Vietnamese Uber driver once said to me, <strong>“don’t waste time when you’re young. When you’re young, you have the most energy. Make the most out of it.”</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What the heck is the Domain Name System (DNS)?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2015/01/16/what-the-heck-is-dns-resolution/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-16T12:20:09-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2015/01/16/what-the-heck-is-dns-resolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>This post was inspired by Monica Dinculescu’s <a href="http://meowni.ca/posts/cat-dns-cascadia/">speech</a> at CUSEC 2015, “The Internet Needs More Cats”.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Internet is so prevalent in our everyday lives but the majority of its users have a very limited understanding of how it works. Admittedly, I am one of them. Recently, I’ve decided to tackle a very small fragment of my Internet ignorance; I wanted to understand how DNS or the Domain Name System works.</p>

<p>DNS is basically the system responsible for translating web addresses such as <code>google.com</code> to IP addresses. These addresses are what’s used internally to identify specific computers among the billions connected over the web. We use domain names instead of IP addresses since the former has a lot more meaning to us as humans and thus are a lot easier to memorize (<code>www.google.com</code> vs <code>http://74.125.224.72/</code>). It’s important to note that DNS, as a service, is not run by any one computer. Instead, the service is offered through an entire network of interconnected computers.</p>

<h2 id="domain-name-syntax">Domain name syntax</h2>

<p>A domain name essentially consists of labels concatenated and delimited by dots. This is just a fancy way to describe the general structure of all the URLs we know and love, like <code>www.facebook.com</code> and <code>www.reddit.com</code>. Each label of a domain name, from right to left, corresponds to a particular level in DNS. For example, the label <code>com</code> is what is generally known as a top level domain or TLD. Other top level domains include <code>ca</code> and <code>cn</code>. Then, the labels <code>facebook</code> or <code>reddit</code> correspond to a lower level in the DNS.</p>

<p>As a side note, there is actually one level above TLDs. This is called the root domain and is represented as a <code>.</code> at the end of all URLs. However, this <code>.</code> is implicit so we usually don’t include it when displaying URLs.</p>

<h2 id="domain-name-space-what-does-all-these-level-stuff-mean">Domain name space (what does all these level stuff mean?)</h2>

<p><img align="right" style="width: 50%" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b1/Domain_name_space.svg" /></p>

<p>The domain name space can be represented as a tree-like structure. Each node represents one particular label in a domain name. The root node would thus correspond to the aforementioned <code>.</code> that is implicitly tagged on to all URLs. TLDs correspond to child nodes of the root node as expected.</p>

<div style="clear: both; margin-bottom: 20px"></div>

<h2 id="practically">Practically…</h2>

<p>A domain name space tree is represented as a distributed database system. DNS name servers, specifically authoritative name servers, assume responsibility over a particular zone in the name space. A zone consists of one or more connected nodes. Each node contains a resource record holding information associated with the current domain name as well as all its child nodes.</p>

<p>As such, to determine an IP address from a domain name, one needs to parse the domain name into the respective labels and traverse the domain name space tree to reach the particular node with the correct IP address.</p>

<h2 id="where-are-all-these-name-servers">Where are all these name servers?</h2>

<p>There are currently <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Root_name_server#Root_server_addresses">13 root name servers</a> located around the world with the majority in the United States. Responsibility of TLD domains is delegated to specific organizations by the Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers (ICANN). For example, the <code>com</code> TLD was originally administered by the United States Department of Defense but is now administered by Verisign. Lower level domains are managed by various other organizations and private entities.</p>

<h2 id="speeding-things-up">Speeding things up</h2>

<p>Having to traverse through the entire domain name space tree everytime you type <code>www.google.com</code> into your browser address bar is super slow. Again, an age old technique called caching is used to speed things up. Typically, alongside the authoritative name servers making up the domain name space tree are recursive name servers. These servers are often provided by Internet Service Providers (ISP) or other organizations such as Google. These servers are the ones your browser will most likely talk to first when it needs to resolve a domain name.</p>

<p>Recursive name servers provide two essential services. First, they are able to perform a DNS recursion over the domain name space tree to resolve a domain name to an IP address. A DNS recursion is basically a recursive traversal over the domain name space tree using information from the domain name to reach the right authoritative name server and obtain the right IP address. A recursive name server only performs a DNS recursion if its local cache does not contain the IP address mapped to a requested domain name. The second service provided by recursive name servers is caching of successful DNS recursion results so that future queries will not require another expensive DNS recursion. Finally, it is also important to note that IP address caching can also happen at the client level AKA on your computer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Euler Angles and Gimbal Lock]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2015/01/06/euler-angles-and-gimbal-lock/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-06T10:09:27-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2015/01/06/euler-angles-and-gimbal-lock</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple months ago, a friend of mine wrote a blog <a href="http://luckytoilet.wordpress.com/2014/11/24/visualizing-quaternions-with-unity/">post</a> about how quarternions solve the problem of gimbal lock in 3D animations (which happens when you use Euler angles). This got me interested in learning more about Euler angles and exactly how gimbal lock works.</p>

<p>Fundamentally, Euler angles are three angles that are used to describe the orientation of a rigid body in 3D space. The rigid body itself has a local coordinate system that is initially aligned with a fixed global coordinate system. Each Euler angle then represents an elemental rotation of that local coordinate system about one of its three axes. From this, it should be understood that any specific elemental rotation will depend on all prior elemental rotations.</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
    <iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/Quvb54gttUg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> 
</div>

<p>There are 12 possible sequences of rotation axes for any set of Euler angles; the most popular of which is what’s commonly referred to as the 3-2-1 set of Euler angles. In aeronautical terms, this set of Euler angles describes, in order, the yaw, pitch, and roll of an aircraft.</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
    <img src="http://www.allstar.fiu.edu/aero/images/pic5-1.gif" />
</div>

<h2 id="gimbal-lock">Gimbal lock</h2>

<p><img align="right" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d5/Gyroscope_operation.gif" /></p>

<p>A gimbal is, according to Wikipedia, a “ring that is suspended so [that] it can rotate about an axis” and gimbals are “typically nested one within another to accomodate rotation about multiple axes”. As such, a nested three-gimbal system can be used to physically model any 3D rotation based on Euler angles.</p>

<p>Gimbal lock occurs when the middle gimbal rotates in such a way that causes the outer and inner gimbals to align in a plane. In this case, rotating both these gimbals in effect only rotates the rigid body on one axis. The resulting system can only rotate on two axes and it has lost one degree of freedom.</p>

<h2 id="gimbal-lock-and-matrices">Gimbal lock and matrices</h2>

<p>Any 2D rotation in 3D space can be described using a matrix. For example, the matrix below represents a rotation about the $z$-axis with a counter-clockwise angle of $\theta$ (a positive angle if you use the right-hand rule).</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{bmatrix}
\cos\theta & -\sin\theta & 0\\
\sin\theta & \cos\theta & 0\\
0 & 0 & 1
\end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;</script>

<p>The gimbal lock problem can be shown mathematically by representing a 3D rotation based on Euler angles with matrices. For a 3-2-1 rotation, the corresponding mathematical expression would be:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
R = 
\begin{bmatrix}1 & 0 & 0 \\ 0 & \cos\alpha & -\sin\alpha\\ 0 & \sin\alpha & \cos\alpha\\\end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix}\cos\beta & 0 & \sin\beta\\ 0 & 1 & 0\\ -\sin\beta & 0 & \cos\beta\end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix}\cos\gamma & -\sin\gamma & 0\\\sin\gamma & \cos\gamma & 0\\0 & 0 & 1\end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;</script>

<p>The rightmost matrix represents a rotation about the $z$-axis (yaw), the middle matrix represents a rotation about the $y$-axis (pitch), and the leftmost matrix represents a rotation about the $x$-axis (roll). If the pitch angle, $\beta$, was set to $\frac{\pi}{2}$, which basically means the aircraft is pointing straight up, we get:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{aligned}
R & = 
\begin{bmatrix}
1 & 0 & 0 \\ 0 & \cos\alpha & -\sin\alpha\\ 0 & \sin\alpha & \cos\alpha\\
\end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix}
0 & 0 & 1\\0 & 1 & 0\\-1 & 0 & 0
\end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix}
\cos\gamma & -\sin\gamma & 0\\\sin\gamma & \cos\gamma & 0\\0 & 0 & 1
\end{bmatrix} \\

& =
\begin{bmatrix}
0 & 0 & 1 \\ \sin\alpha\cos\gamma + \cos\alpha\sin\gamma & -\sin\alpha\cos\gamma + \cos\alpha\sin\gamma & 0\\ -\cos\alpha\cos\gamma + \sin\alpha\sin\gamma & \cos\alpha\cos\gamma + \sin\alpha\sin\gamma & 0\\
\end{bmatrix} \\

& = 
\begin{bmatrix}
0 & 0 & 1 \\ \sin(\alpha + \gamma) & \cos(\alpha + \gamma) & 0\\ -\cos(\alpha + \gamma) & \sin(\alpha + \gamma) & 0\\
\end{bmatrix}
\end{aligned} %]]&gt;</script>

<p>From the above matrix, you can tell that in this state, there is no distinction between yaw and pitch. Applying one change to the yaw angle has the exact effect on the orientation of the aircraft as applying the same change to the roll angle. The system has lost one degree of freedom.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Although I’ve only mathematically shown how gimbal lock occurs in a 3-2-1 system, it is important to note that there is always the possibility of gimbal lock in any other rotation axes sequence. This is a fundamental problem for Euler angles as the map from Euler angles to rotations is not a covering map. In layman’s terms, this means that it is not possible to use Euler angles to represent every 3D rotation. Specifically, for certain values of the second angle, gimbal lock will occur.</p>

<p>Gimbal lock in Euler angles is of practical concern today particularly in the fields of 3D animations and robotics. When it does occur, it leads to weird and undesirable rotation artifacts. Fortunately, there are multiple solutions to this problem. Mechanically, gimbal lock can be solved by adding a fourth gimbal. For 3D animations, a popular solution is to use quarternions instead of Euler angles in calculating rotations.</p>

<p>If, for any reason, you are still confused about what gimbal lock is or how it works, I definitely recommend watching this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zc8b2Jo7mno">video</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bijective numeration and length-restricted character permutations]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2014/12/31/bijective-numeration-and-length-restricted-character-permuations/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-31T18:37:41-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2014/12/31/bijective-numeration-and-length-restricted-character-permuations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Based on this awesome StackOverflow <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/15625853">answer</a>…</p>

<p>Consider the problem where you have a size $N$ set of characters and you need to the generate all possible strings from this set that have length less than or equal to $M$.</p>

<p>Let’s represent the set of characters programmatically as a character array. In this array, each character is mapped to an integer index starting from 0 all the way to $N - 1$. Now consider a base-$N$ numeral system. In this system, there are $N$ symbols to represent the $N$ numbers below 10. We also know that in this system, $N^M - 1$ will evaluate to the largest number that has a string representation of length $M$. So to generate all strings with length less than or equal to $M$, we could just enumerate from 0 to $N^M - 1$ in base $N$ and for each base-$N$ integer, we can create a valid string by replacing each digit of the integer with the character that has the same array index.</p>

<p>For example, if the character array was <code>{'a', 'b', 'c', '3'}</code> and a base-4 number was 312, the equivalent string is <code>3bc</code>.</p>

<p>However, there is a slight problem with this. The strings generated are missing strings with multiple leading characters that is the first character in the array (AKA the character mapped to the 0 index). This is because when you’re iterating from 0 to $N^M - 1$, you would never reach $0000$, for example, since this is just 0. From the above example, that means that you’re missing the string <code>aaaa</code>, even though it is a perfectly valid string if 4 is less than or equal to $M$.</p>

<p>This is where a bijective numeration becomes helpful. A bijective numeration, according to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bijective_numeration">Wikipedia</a> is: “any numeral system in which every non-negative integer can be represented in exactly one way using a finite string of digits”.</p>

<p>Conventional numeral systems often have multiple ways to represent the same integer and thus are not bijective. For example, in the numeral system that we’re all familiar with, the Hindu-Arabic numeral system, you can represent the integer 1 an infinite number of ways just by tacking any number of 0’s in front of it. A bijective base-k numeration system ($k$-adic notation) circumvents this by getting rid of the symbol 0 altogether. The value 0 is represented with the empty string, $\varepsilon$. A digit-set of {1, 2, …, k} is used to represent the rest of the positive integers. So, for example, 11110 in base-8 would be represented as 8888 in $k$-adic notation.</p>

<h2 id="from-base-10-to-k-adic-notation">From base-10 to $k$-adic notation</h2>

<p>So, given the understanding of $k$-adic notation, the problem can be solved with a character array where index 0 is mapped to nothing and indices start at 1. We then iterate from 1 to $N^M + N^{M - 1} + \ldots + N$ and convert each integer from base-10 to the $k$-adic notation equivalent before generating the particular string ($N^M + N^{M - 1} + \ldots + N$ is the largest number that has a string representation of length $M$ in $N$-adic). The only question left is how do we convert from base-10 to $k$-adic.</p>

<p>The algorithm is as complex as the algorithm that converts base-10 to base-$N$. Suppose $x$ is the base-10 number we need to convert from and the $k$-adic equivalent is represented by the digit-string $a_n a_{n_1} \ldots a_1 a_0$, then:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
a_0 & = x - q_0 k, q_0 = \lceil \frac{x}{k} \rceil - 1 \\
a_1 & = q_0 - q_1 k, q_1 = \lceil \frac{q_0}{k} \rceil - 1 \\
& \ldots \\
a_n & = q_{n-1} - 0k, q_n = \lceil \frac{q_{n-1}}{k} \rceil - 1 = 0
\end{align} %]]&gt;</script>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notes on Binary Indexed Trees (Fenwick Trees)]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2014/12/27/notes-on-binary-indexed-trees/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-27T13:52:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2014/12/27/notes-on-binary-indexed-trees</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A binary indexed tree came up in one of the Hackerrank challenges I was working on recently. This is the first time I’ve ever heard of this data structure and I was interested in learning more. I found this TopCoder <a href="http://community.topcoder.com/tc?module=Static&amp;d1=tutorials&amp;d2=binaryIndexedTrees">article</a> on binary indexed trees a particularly useful resource and below is a concise summary of what I’ve learnt.</p>

<p>Suppose we have a size-$n$ array of values. If we wanted to find the summation of all values between two indices, we would need to iterate through the entire interval while maintaining a summation variable. If we then wanted to make $m$ such queries, the time complexity of the whole operation would be $O(mn)$. A binary indexed tree allows us to do this in $O(m\log\ n)$ time. The one trade off is that it takes longer to construct the initial data structure ($O(n \log\ n)$ time instead of $O(n)$ time, which is if we had used an array).</p>

<p>Internally, we will still be using a size-$n$ array to represent the tree. The <strong>main idea</strong> of a binary indexed tree is that indices that are a power of 2 will have the cumulative frequency of all indices before, including itself. Indices that are half way between two indices that are a power of 2 will have the cumulative frequency of all indices before it starting from, but not including, the lower power of 2 index. This pattern continues down a hierarchical structure until you reach an odd index which will only have the frequency of itself. This can be visualized with the following diagram from the aforementioned article:</p>

<p><img align="right" src="http://community.topcoder.com/i/education/binaryIndexedTrees/bitval.gif" alt="Binary indexed tree visualization" /></p>

<p>Another way to put this is that each index $i$ in a binary indexed tree stores the sum of all frequencies of the indices in the range $(i - 2^r, i]$ where $r$ represents the rightmost set bit of $i$. From this definition, it is easier to tell that an index that is a power of 2 will have the sum of all frequencies of the indices before it while an odd index will just contain the frequency of itself.</p>

<p><strong>Note:</strong> for a binary indexed tree, internally, the starting index is $1$ and not $0$</p>

<h2 id="isolating-the-rightmost-set-bit-of-a-number">Isolating the rightmost set bit of a number</h2>

<p>Given the structure of the binary indexed tree, many of its operations will often need to find and isolate the rightmost set bit of a number. As such, we need to be able to do this efficiently.</p>

<p>Any nonzero binary number can be represented in the form $(a)(1)(0..0)$, where $a$ is the rest of the binary number to the left of the rightmost set bit. To isolate the rightmost set bit of one such number (call it $x$), we need to use its two’s complement representation.</p>

<p>To get the two’s complement representation of a number, all we need to do is invert every bit and add $1$ to the result. So if $x = (a)(1)(0..0)$, then the two’s complement representation of $x$ will be $(a^{-})(1)(0..0)$. Bitwise ANDing the two binary numbers together will then result in $(0..0)(1)(0..0)$. This is exactly what we want!</p>

<p>Most computers in the world represent negative integers using two’s complement so all we need to do in code is <code>x &amp; -x</code>.</p>

<h2 id="finding-the-cumulative-frequency-for-a-particular-index">Finding the cumulative frequency for a particular index</h2>

<p>Suppose we want to find the cumulative frequency from index $1$ to a particular index $x$. We know that at index $x$, the tree stores the cumulative frequency of the indices in the interval $(x - 2^r, x]$.</p>

<p>So to find the cumulative frequency of the indices in $[1, x]$, we first add <code>binary_index_tree[x]</code> to a summation variable and subtract the rightmost set bit of $x$ from itself. Now if we query for <code>binary_index_tree[x]</code> again, we get the cumulative frequency of all indices between $(x - 2^r - 2^{r_1}, x - 2^r]$. When we add the new <code>binary_index_tree[x]</code> to the summation variable, we get the cumulative frequencies of indices between $(x - 2^r - 2^{r_1}, x]$. We keep repeating this process until the left endpoint of the interval becomes $0$, which is when we have our answer.</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class="line-number">1</span>
<span class="line-number">2</span>
<span class="line-number">3</span>
<span class="line-number">4</span>
<span class="line-number">5</span>
<span class="line-number">6</span>
<span class="line-number">7</span>
<span class="line-number">8</span>
</pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="java"><span class="line"><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">read</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class="line">    <span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">sum</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">;</span>
</span><span class="line">    <span class="k">while</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class="line">        <span class="n">sum</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="n">binary_index_tree</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">];</span>
</span><span class="line">        <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">-=</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">);</span>
</span><span class="line">    <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class="line">    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">sum</span><span class="o">;</span>
</span><span class="line"><span class="o">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>

<p>Since the max index you can query for is $n$ (which is the total size of the data set) and it can have a maximum of $\log\ n$ set bits, the <code>read</code> function’s time complexity is $O(\log\ n)$.</p>

<h2 id="changing-frequency-of-a-particular-index">Changing frequency of a particular index</h2>

<p>To change a frequency at a particular index $x$, we also need to change the values of all indices that contain it. All such indices will be greater than $x$.</p>

<div class="bogus-wrapper"><notextile><figure class="code"><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class="line-number">1</span>
<span class="line-number">2</span>
<span class="line-number">3</span>
<span class="line-number">4</span>
<span class="line-number">5</span>
<span class="line-number">6</span>
</pre></td><td class="code"><pre><code class="java"><span class="line"><span class="kt">void</span> <span class="nf">update</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">val</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class="line">    <span class="k">while</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">idx</span> <span class="o">&lt;=</span> <span class="n">n</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class="line">        <span class="n">binary_index_tree</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="n">idx</span><span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="n">val</span><span class="o">;</span>
</span><span class="line">        <span class="n">idx</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">idx</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">idx</span><span class="o">);</span>
</span><span class="line">    <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class="line"><span class="o">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>

<p>Since we are iterating to $n$ and we’re adding the rightmost set bit of the current index to itself at each iteration, the <code>update</code> function’s time complexity is also $O(\log\ n)$.</p>

<h2 id="other-operations">Other operations</h2>

<p>I’ve only written about the two most basic operations you can do with a binary indexed tree. If you would like to learn more, the TopCoder article I mentioned above provides indepth explanations into many others.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notes on RSA Cryptography]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2014/12/06/notes-on-rsa/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-06T16:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2014/12/06/notes-on-rsa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I first learnt about RSA cryptography during an introductory number theory course in my second study term in university. Like many things you learn in class, the details tend to quickly be forgotten once the exam’s over. RSA was no exception. However, I’ve always been strangely annoyed for not fully understanding how this cryptosystem works and so I intend for this post to act as a “reference sheet” for RSA.</p>

<p>In RSA cryptography, there are two keys: a public key and a private key. The sender of a message uses the public key to encrypt the message and the idea is that you can only decrypt the message if you have the private key associated with that public key.</p>

<h2 id="generating-keys">Generating keys</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Select two <strong>large</strong> distinct primes $p$ and $q$. Let $n = pq$</li>
  <li>Select $e \in \mathbb{Z}$ such that $GCD(e, \phi(n)) = 1$ and $1 \lt e \lt \phi(n)$, where $GCD$ is the greatest common denominator function</li>
  <li>Solve congruence $ed \equiv 1 (\textrm{mod}\ \phi(n))$ for $d$ where $d \in \mathbb{Z}, 1 &lt; d &lt; \phi(n)$</li>
</ol>

<p>The public key will be the tuple $(e, n)$ and the private key will be the tuple $(d, n)$. Note, $\phi(n)$ here refers to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%27s_totient_function">Euler’s totient function</a>, which is the number of positive integers less than or equal to n that are coprime with n. It also has the property that if two integers, $m$ and $n$ are coprime, then $\phi(mn) = \phi(m)\phi(n)$. Using this property and the fact that $p$ and $q$ are coprimes (since they are both primes), we note that $\phi(n) = \phi(pq) = \phi(p)\phi(q) = (p - 1)(q - 1)$.</p>

<h2 id="encrypting-and-decrypting-messages">Encrypting and decrypting messages</h2>

<p>Let $M$ be the message we want to encrypt. $M$ is an integer such that $0 \leq M \lt n$. The encrypted message will be $C$ where $C \equiv M^{e} (\textrm{mod}\ n), 0 \leq C \lt n $.</p>

<p>To decrypt the message, the receiver needs to compute integer $R$ where $R \equiv C^{d} (\textrm{mod}\ n), 0 \leq R \lt n$. It is actually the case that $R \equiv M (\textrm{mod}\ n)$ and since $0 \leq R \lt n$, $R = M$.</p>

<p>Overall, we need to prove that $(M^{e})^{d} \equiv M (\textrm{mod}\ n), \forall M \in \mathbb{Z}$.</p>

<h2 id="proof">Proof</h2>

<p>(This proof is really just my version of <a href="http://crypto.stackexchange.com/questions/2884/rsa-proof-of-correctness">this</a>)</p>

<p>We can break the proof into two cases, $GCD(M, n) = 1$ and $GCD(M, n) \neq 1$.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Case 1 ($GCD(M, n) = 1$):</strong></p>

<p>We start off by using Euler’s totient theorem which states that:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If $GCD(A, B) = 1$ then $A^{\phi(B)} \equiv 1 (\textrm{mod}\ B)$. In our case, since $GCD(M, n) = 1$, then $M^{\phi(n)} \equiv 1 (\textrm{mod}\ n)$.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Since $ed \equiv 1 (\textrm{mod}\ \phi(n))$, then let $ed = 1 + k\phi(n)$ where $k \in \mathbb{Z}$. From this, we get that:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">(M^{e})^{d} = M^{ed} = M^{1 + k\phi(n)} = M(M^{k\phi(n)})</script>

<p>Using the above fact:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
M^{\phi(n)} & \equiv 1 (\textrm{mod}\ n) \\
M^{k\phi(n)} & \equiv 1^{k} (\textrm{mod}\ n) \\
M^{k\phi(n)} & \equiv 1 (\textrm{mod}\ n) \\
M(M^{k\phi(n)}) & \equiv M (\textrm{mod}\ n) \\
M^{ed} & \equiv M (\textrm{mod}\ n)
\end{align} %]]&gt;</script>

<hr />

<p><strong>Case 2 ($GCD(M, n) \neq 1$):</strong></p>

<p>We will use the Chinese remainder theorem to prove this.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A more specific version of the theorem states that:</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
x & \equiv y (\textrm{mod}\ A_1) \\
& ... \\
x & \equiv y (\textrm{mod}\ A_k) \\
\\
\text{if and only if...} \\
\\
x & \equiv y (\textrm{mod}\ A)
\end{align} %]]&gt;</script>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>where $A_1, …, A_k$ are <strong>pairwise</strong> coprime and $A = A_1…A_k$.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>By the Chinese remainder theorem, we only need to prove the two congruences below to prove $(M^{e})^{d} \equiv M (\textrm{mod}\ n)$:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\begin{align}
(M^{e})^{d} \equiv M (\textrm{mod}\ p)\tag{1} \\
(M^{e})^{d} \equiv M (\textrm{mod}\ q)\tag{2}
\end{align}</script>

<p>Since $GCD(M, n) \neq 1$, it must be true that either $GCD(M, n) = p$ or $GCD(M, n) = q$.</p>

<p>Without loss of generality, let’s assume that $GCD(M, n) = p$. Since $M$ is a multiple of $p$, let $M = kp, k \in \mathbb{Z}, k \gt 0$.</p>

<p>To prove (1):</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
M & \equiv kp (\textrm{mod}\ p) \\
M & \equiv 0 (\textrm{mod}\ p) \\
\\
\text{Using the above fact...} \\
\\
(M^{e})^{d} & \equiv M (\textrm{mod}\ p) \\
((kp)^{e})^{d} & \equiv M (\textrm{mod}\ p) \\
k^{ed}p^{ed} & \equiv 0 (\textrm{mod}\ p) \\
0 & \equiv 0 (\textrm{mod}\ p)
\end{align} %]]&gt;</script>

<p>For (2), we note that since $M = kp$, if $q$ divides $M$, then $q$ must divide either $k$ or $p$. $q$ cannot divide $p$ since they are both primes and $q$ cannot divide $k$. If $q$ does divide $k$, then it implies $M \geq n$ which $M$ cannot be. We reach the conclusion that $GCD(M, q) = 1$. By Euler’s totient theorem, $M^{\phi(q)} = M^{q - 1} \equiv 1 (\textrm{mod}\ q)$.</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
(M^{e})^{d} & = M^{ed} \\
& = M^{ed - 1}M \\
& = M^{k\phi(n)}M\tag{from before} \\
& = (M^{q - 1})^{k(p - 1)}M \\
& \equiv 1^{k(p - 1)}M (\textrm{mod}\ q) \\
& \equiv M (\textrm{mod}\ q)\tag*{$\square$}
\end{align} %]]&gt;</script>

<h2 id="why-is-rsa-secure">Why is RSA secure?</h2>

<p>The answer to this question lies in the fact that it is nearly impossible (by our current computing capabilities) to determine the private key from its corresponding public key, especially if the primes chosen are sufficiently large.</p>

<p>If the public key was $(e, n)$, then remember that to determine the private key you need to solve the congruence $ed \equiv 1 (\textrm{mod}\ \phi(n)), 1 \lt d \lt \phi(n)\ \text{and}\ \phi(n) = (p - 1)(q - 1)$. The best way to do so, without actually knowing what $\phi(n)$ is, is to prime factorize $n$ into its only two prime factors. This, as it turns out, is a very very hard thing to do. There <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integer_factorization">doesn’t exist an algorithm</a> (with the exception of quantum algorithms) that can solve the problem in polynomial time.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I made a movie about cosmic cookware. It was universally panned.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some notes on the Mercator projection]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2014/11/29/some-notes-on-the-mercator-projection/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-29T22:22:42-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2014/11/29/some-notes-on-the-mercator-projection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while back I was investigating on how I would build a Twitter mapping application similar to the <a href="http://www.onemilliontweetmap.com/">One Million Tweet Map</a> project. One of the first topics I looked into was how I would plot and display each tweet on a map. I was hesitant on using the Google Maps API and wanted to build the project on top of the HTML5 Canvas.</p>

<p>The main challenge here was implementing an algorithm that would map latitude and longitude information into x and y coordinates onto the canvas. I looked into several map projections and decided to settle on the Mercator projection (arguably the most commonly used map projection in the world). I did a little bit of research into Mercator projections with the help of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mercator_projection">Wikipedia</a> and here is a concise summary of what I’ve learnt.</p>

<p>The Mercator projection is a cylindrical map projection. This means that meridians are mapped to equally spaced vertical lines and circles of latitudes are mapped to equally spaced horizontal lines. The projection assumes that the Earth is a perfect sphere (in truth the Earth is best modelled by an oblate spheroid). Our map will be a Mercator projection of a scaled down version of the perfectly spherical Earth. This scaled down version of the Earth will be called the globe and it has a radius $R$.</p>

<p>The Mercator projection can be understood using small element geometry. The idea is that if we “unwrap” the globe and spread it flat as best we could, very small elements or sections on the globe can be modelled using a rectangle. The diagram below visualizes this idea ($\lambda$ represents the longitude and $\phi$ represents the latitude).</p>

<p><img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d0/CylProj_infinitesimals2.svg" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<p>The perpendicular distance from the axis of rotation to any point on the globe at latitude $\phi$ is $R \cdot \cos\phi$ and so we get $R \cdot \cos\phi \cdot \delta\lambda$ as the horizontal distance between $P$ and $Q$ using the arc length formula.</p>

<p>The vertical distance between $P$ and $Q$ can also be explained using the same logic. Since latitudes are measured from the center of the globe and the difference in latitude between $P$ and $Q$ is $\delta\phi$, using the arc length formula again gives us $R \cdot \delta\phi$.</p>

<p>With this information, we define two scale factors from globe to cylinder:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
k(\phi) & =\frac{P'M'}{PM}=\frac{\delta x}{R \cdot \cos\phi \cdot \delta\lambda}\tag{parallel scale factor} \\
h(\phi) & =\frac{P'K'}{PK}=\frac{\delta y}{R \cdot \delta\phi}\tag{meridian scale factor}
\end{align} %]]&gt;</script>

<h2 id="mapping-from-longitudes-to-x-coordinates">Mapping from longitudes to x coordinates</h2>

<p>We note that for small $\delta\lambda$, $\delta x = R \cdot \delta\lambda$. From this equation, we can obtain the mapping function from longitudes to x coordinates (one half of the Mercator projection). $\delta x = R \cdot \delta\lambda$ is a very simple rearranged first order linear differential equation and we can solve it quickly.</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
\delta x & = R \cdot \delta\lambda \\
\int \delta x & = R \cdot \int \delta\lambda \\
x + c_1 & = R \cdot (\lambda + c_2) \\
x & = (R \cdot \lambda) + (R \cdot c_2) - c_1 \\
& = R(\lambda - \lambda_0)
\end{align} %]]&gt;</script>

<p>Here $\lambda_0$ is the longitude of an arbitrary central meridian (this is usually Greenwich).</p>

<h2 id="mapping-from-latitudes-to-y-coordinates">Mapping from latitudes to y coordinates</h2>

<p>Before starting, it is important to understand that the Mercator projection is conformal. This means that the projection of points from the globe to the cylinder preserves angles. This property can be defined in two ways:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Equality of angles $\beta = \alpha$</li>
  <li>Isotropy of scale factors: $h = k$</li>
</ol>

<p>From the above, we know that $\delta x = R \cdot \delta\lambda$ and substituting this into the expression for $k(\phi)$ gets us:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
\frac{1}{\cos\phi} & = k(\phi) \\
& = h(\phi)\tag{from (2)} \\
& = \frac{\delta y}{R \cdot \delta\phi} \\
\frac{\delta y}{\delta\phi} & = R \cdot \sec\phi
\end{align} %]]&gt;</script>

<p>Solving this differential equation gives us the mapping function from latitudes to y coordinates:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">y = R \cdot \ln[\tan(\frac{\pi}{4} + \frac{\phi}{2})]</script>

<h2 id="finding-the-radius-of-the-globe-r">Finding the radius of the globe, $R$</h2>

<p>But wait, there’s more! All this time we’ve been working with the radius of the globe, $R$, but what exactly is it’s value once we put the projection into practice?</p>

<p>Since the Mercator projection is cylindrical, the scale factor between the globe and the cylinder equals one only at the equator. This means that the circumference of the cylinder will equal the circumference of the globe and so the horizontal length of the physical map will equal $2 \cdot \pi \cdot R$.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Finally, we can define the Mercator projection with these three equations (where z equals the horizontal length of the physical map):</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{align}
R & = \frac{z}{2 \cdot \pi} \\
x & = R(\lambda - \lambda_0) \\
y & = R \cdot \ln[\tan(\frac{\pi}{4} + \frac{\phi}{2})]
\end{align} %]]&gt;</script>

<h2 id="inaccuracies-with-the-projection">Inaccuracies with the projection</h2>

<p>Interestingly, despite being one of the most popular projections in the world, the Mercator projection is grossly inaccurate in representing the relative sizes of different land masses. In particular, land masses get bloated the closer to the poles you go up to a point where the projection is not even capable of displaying the poles.</p>

<p><img src="http://media.economist.com/sites/default/files/imagecache/original-size/20101113_WOM943.gif" alt="Alt text" /></p>

<p>This weird property of the projection can be understood by examining the parallel scale factor ($k(\phi)=\frac{\delta x}{R \cdot \cos\phi \cdot \delta\lambda}$). As we approach the poles, the latitudes approach $\pm 90^o$ and we know that $\cos\phi$ approaches $0$. Since $\cos\phi$ is in the denominator of the scale factor, the factor approaches $\infty$. An accurate projection will require the parallel scale factor to be $1$ everywhere.</p>

<p>This explains why land masses closer to the poles get bloated while the poles cannot be represented since they would technically have infinite width on the projection.</p>

<hr />

<h5 id="sidenote">Sidenote</h5>

<p>We can derive the latitude mapping function a second way.</p>

<p>For small elements, we note that $\measuredangle PKQ$ is a right angle and so we get the two equations:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\begin{aligned}
\tan\delta = \frac{R \cdot \cos\phi \cdot \delta\lambda}{R \cdot \delta\phi}, \tan\beta = \frac{\delta x}{\delta y}
\end{aligned}</script>

<p>From $(1)$ equality of angles, we get the equation $\frac{R \cdot \cos\phi \cdot \delta\lambda}{R \cdot \delta\phi} = \frac{\delta x}{\delta y}$. We also know that $\delta x = R \cdot \delta\lambda$ for small elements. Using the latter fact and rearranging the former equation, we again reach $\frac{\delta y}{\delta\phi} = R \cdot \sec\phi$.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Two random variables were talking in a bar. They thought they were being discrete but I heard their chatter continuously</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
