<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Mango Ice Cream]]></title>
  <link href="http://kevinpan.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kevinpan.me/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-12T04:08:09-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://kevinpan.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kevin Pan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I overcame anxiety and depression]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/03/12/how-i-overcame-anxiety-and-depression/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-12T02:48:25-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/03/12/how-i-overcame-anxiety-and-depression</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Test</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick Tips For a Healthier Lifestyle as a College Student]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevinpan.me/blog/2015/05/17/quick-tips-for-a-healthier-lifestyle-as-a-college-student/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-17T20:48:56-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2015/05/17/quick-tips-for-a-healthier-lifestyle-as-a-college-student</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For many of us, going to college means living away from home for the first time. There are many other firsts that come with moving out… you might have to start doing your own laundry for the first time, or start cooking your own dinners. As a third year university student, I’ve been through all these firsts and learned quite a few things along the way.</p>

<p>One of the best things about living away from home is the freedom. You get to do whatever you want now without having parents nosing around. But that also means the possibility of developing unhealthy lifestyle habits, especially dietary habits, that you might regret later on.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What people are not good at, though, is identifying what’s missing in their diet, mainly because people don’t typically think of these things.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Let me first focus on dietary habits. When it comes to your diet, it’s important to realize that it doesn’t necessarily have to be what you’re eating that makes it unhealthy, it could also be from what you’re NOT eating. I think everyone’s pretty good at identifying generally unhealthy foods (e.g. greasy, sugary, starchy, …) so I won’t elaborate on this. What people are not good at, though, is identifying what’s missing in their diet, mainly because people don’t typically think of these things. Back home, your parents made your food and you ate it. So my best diet advice for you is to keep in mind what nutrients you might have missed out on in your current diet. When I say nutrients I mean things like calcium, iron, vitamin B, and vitamin D.</p>

<p>An extra comment on diet. It’s always good to keep in mind there are some foods that are just so much more efficient than others at giving you the nutrients you need. For example, nuts and seeds are packed with protein, vitamins, and minerals. Find these foods, eat them regularly.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And you can’t fault people for this; exercise is painful. Cardio is hard on both the mind and the body, weight lifting is strenuous.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Besides a healthy diet, a healthy lifestyle also warrants that you stay physically active (I know, how generic, who doesn’t know this?). Truth is, people do know this but many people don’t act on it. And you can’t fault people for this; exercise is painful. Cardio is hard on both the mind and the body, weight lifting is strenuous. Okay, maybe weight lifting is an exception, since having bulging muscles is strong enough motivation to keep many guys going back to the gym. But cardio, in my experience, is something many people shy away from. Like I mentioned, it’s not easy. You’re often uncomfortable physically and bored out of your mind on that treadmill or elliptical. For me personally, I’ve made cardio, specifically running, a key part of my lifestyle. I’ve run enough times to not have to deal with the physical discomfort part but it’s still often quite boring.</p>

<p>But no worries, it doesn’t have to be this way. There’s another form of exercise I learned recently that, apparently, is significantly better than steady-state cardio. It’s called High Intensity Interval Training (HIIT). Most often applied to running, what it means is to break your running sessions into multiple sprinting and resting periods. For example, you would sprint 1 minute, rest 1 minute, and so forth. This type of exercise burns calories at a much faster rate than steady-state cardio and, as claimed by countless resources online, is just plain better. No matter the calorie burning rate, one thing that’s for sure is that HIIT is not boring. You’re constantly changing your pace so it’s not monotonous and segmenting your workout session into 1 or 2 minute increments make it go by a lot faster. This, to me, is one of the best things about HIIT.</p>

<p>Now that you have a wholesome diet and you’re in love with HIIT and exercising frequently, you must think that you’re all set for a healthy lifestyle right? Yes you are. Why are you still reading?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…a healthy lifestyle isn’t all about being physically healthy. You have to be mentally healthy too.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>No I’m kidding, a healthy lifestyle isn’t all about being physically healthy. You have to be mentally healthy too. What do I mean by this? Well, sometimes, instead of binging on TV shows like Game of Thrones or Breaking Bad or Suits, you might choose to read something that holds more weight, like… the biography of Steve Jobs (Steve Jobs, by Walter Isaacson, great read, I recommend it). I guess the best advice I can give is to make sure you’re PASSIONATE about at least something in life and you’re actively working on improving that thing you’re passionate about. If you aren’t and you find yourself watching too many TV shows or movies or playing too many videos games or partying, maybe you should find that passion.</p>

<p>One of the most common advice I’ve heard from people much older, much wiser than I is to NOT WASTE TIME when you’re young. Time is precious and it might feel like you have a lot now, but it goes by exponentially as you age. And yes, you’ve heard this before, excuse me for being so cliché, but many people simply don’t do anything about it. Don’t be like “many people”, lead a purposeful life.</p>

<p>A middle-aged Vietnamese Uber driver once said to me, <strong>“don’t waste time when you’re young. When you’re young, you have the most energy. Make the most out of it.”</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
