<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mango Ice Cream</title>
    <description>Avid road cyclist. Aspiring product manager. Passionate software developer. Armchair political scientist. Couch economist.
</description>
    <link>http://kevinpan.me/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://kevinpan.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 23:06:04 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 23:06:04 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Case Study: Dumbest Idea to Grow a Website</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/vCMKf14.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like playing Teamfight Tactics, an “autochess” game released by Riot Games a few months ago. At first, I played it casually but I started climbing the ranked ladder quickly. Before I knew it, I was top 1000 NA, and then top 500, and at some point top 300. The higher I climbed, the more addicted I was and the more time I sank into the game. When I spend so much time on something, I like to channel the addiction into a productive venture. That’s why I built StoreOfValueBlog.com when I was learning about cryptocurrencies, and why I built SmashVODs.tv when I played Smash. For TFT, I built AutochessTV.com. However, I had to sunset the website in favor of TwitchHighlights.tv, but there was no way I would stop doing stuff for TFT… I’m hopelessly addicted. As such, inspired by articles posted on /r/CompetitiveTFT, I recently started a TFT blog called TFTeacher.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/pQsK1N7.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of building websites is getting consistent and cheap (i.e. free) traffic. Without traffic, a website is useless. With traffic, it’s a gold mine. Attention is a highly valuable commodity (e.g. Facebook charges about &lt;span&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;7 per 1000 ad impressions and &lt;span&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;1 per ad click). Competition is fierce and it’s a monumental task building a consistent traffic source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google’s search engine is the best traffic source. Ranking highly on popular search terms translates to a huge amount of consistent and free traffic. Unfortunately, securing Google search traffic is very competitive, mostly because there’s usually only one first page for a Google search term. You need to do very creative things to win. If you don’t, someone else will and your links get pushed down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve done some very unconventional stuff to grow TwitchQuotes.com and StoreOfValueBlog.com. TwitchQuotes.com now ranks 1st and 2nd for the search term “copypastas”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image outline-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/cCOa309.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For TFTeacher.com, I had the dumbest idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of just posting articles to Reddit to grow the blog’s Google search rank, why not create a TFT account with the website’s URL as its username, climb TFT’s ranked ladder, and get into games with popular high elo TFT streamers? It &lt;s&gt;sounds&lt;/s&gt; is dumb… I’ve never seen anyone advertise a website with their username, only their Twitch streams. But it wasn’t dumb enough to dissuade me from trying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did. I created an account called TFTEACHERºCOM and started climbing ranked. A couple days in, I managed to get into a series of 3 games with Scarra, the top TFT streamer on Twitch. I was pleasantly surprised by the results. Not only did TFTeacher.com get a decent amount of visitors during the games, there were also unexpected transient effects. Scarra uploaded one of the games with TFTEACHERºCOM to YouTube and the website continues to get nontrivial steady-state traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/JiZD9rO.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image outline-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/Nef3aHp.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was not only an interesting exercise to find an unconventionally effective way to drive traffic to a website, it was also a fun experience. TFTEACHERºCOM was in 3 of Scarra’s games on-stream. He had about 7k concurrent viewers during that time. For the sake of experimenting with advertising TFTeacher.com, I tried to be memorable (without passing the fine line of being annoying) in in-game chat. It was also helpful that in one game, Scarra and I were the last two players alive and I was able to eke out a win. The final moments of that game gave the TFTEACHERºCOM username significant airtime and attention. In another game, DisguisedToast (another large TFT streamer), who was in voice chat with Scarra, commented on my username on stream. Toast mentioned something about the top player in the lobby shilling a website with his username… TRUE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-iframe&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;iframe-parent&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://clips.twitch.tv/embed?clip=CarefulEvilTigerFUNgineer&amp;amp;autoplay=false&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reception to TFTEACHERºCOM’s appearance on stream was varied but generally positive. Some people laughed at the stupid joke I always make in in-game chat, some people thought it was cringe. It doesn’t matter, as long as it wasn’t too annoying, I want the memorability. Here’s an example of Scarra’s chat at the end of a game I won. Someone said “TFTEACHER SENPAI”, another person said “that teacher was op”, and someone else said “no one go to that website. it’s cringe”. My favorite chat message is definitely “imagine shilling your website LUL”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night, I was matched with another large TFT streamer (Keane) and one of the players in the game mentioned that they saw me on Scarra’s YouTube video. I told the same Twisted Fate joke again and I was told to get a new joke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did Twisted Fate get deported? Because he doesn’t have a green card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/A2EpNVl.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 04:14:12 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2019/11/28/case-study-dumbest-idea-to-grow-a-website/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kevinpan.me/blog/2019/11/28/case-study-dumbest-idea-to-grow-a-website/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I&#39;m Fixing Me o.o</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/lb8r3e0.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2019 has been a wild ride. So much has happened and every time I think back, I’m surprised that it’s still 2019. Of all the things I’ve done this year, I’m most satisfied with my progress in dealing with anxiety. It’s been a long uphill battle against the big A ever since its onset during middle school, and even though it has abated in recent years, it remains occasionally debilitating. This year, I’ve made significant inroads in quelling the beast. Here’s what I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving in, I should describe what anxiety means for me since it manifests differently in different people. My anxiety can be succinctly described as an intense fear of loss. During bouts of anxiety, my brain focuses on one or two things I care about deeply and I get scared that I’d lose them. It’s just a little bit weird and awkward o.o These episodes are stressful and annoying to deal with. I can’t concentrate nor enjoy the things I normally would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, tackling anxiety became an exercise of understanding emotions and controlling them by adjusting external factors. I focused on doing things that uplifted my mood and engaging my mind to keep it distracted from anxiety. The three most effective ways I did so were: (1) experimenting and controlling my diet, (2) following a regimented exercise routine, and (3) leaning into entrepreneurial inclinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone’s physiology is slightly different and I experimented (and continue to experiment) with different diets to learn what works for my body. I focused on adjusting eating schedules, adjusting macronutrient ratios, and testing different supplements. When something works, it comes with notable benefits to my mood and physical health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mild intermittent fasting (i.e. skipping breakfast and lunch) is great. An empty digestive tract just feels cleaner and healthier, allowing me to stay focused throughout the day. It’s also great for controlling caloric intake since you only need to plan one meal. I still have a voracious appetite… it’s just easier to control when I’m used to intermittent fasting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supplements are helpful and cost effective. I identified nutrients I was probably deficient on and tried taking them as supplements. Only a few had noticeable effects, most had none. What’s important is finding the tiny subset that works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I also experimented with macronutrient ratios. Reducing carbohydrate intake and increasing fat intake works wonders (it’s generally beneficial if the Internet is to be believed). I don’t take it to the extreme though; ketosis is not for me and carbs are too delicious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;regimented-exercise-routine&quot;&gt;Regimented exercise routine&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out, exercise is great. Who knew?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put myself on a regimented daily exercise routine, alternating between weight training and cardio days. The routine was easy to follow since my apartment has a gym (unofficially 24/7) and my commute to work is short. Keeping up with this schedule has untold benefits for my mood. This is especially true for cardio. Long distance running is like a convenient dopamine tap when you find a distance and pace that’s strenous but also comfortable to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;building-sht&quot;&gt;Building sh*t&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an entrepreneurial streak and leaning into it distracts my mind from anxiety. When I’m excited about building a product or growing a business, it’s very easy to channel my anxious energy to working on the idea. Over the past year, there was not a single moment when I was not actively building something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to think about how things would be different without anxiety… but maybe it’s better to have lived with and overcomed it than not ¯\&lt;em&gt;(ツ)&lt;/em&gt;/¯ Anxiety is probably never fully conquerable, but I can make it inconsequential.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 01:37:24 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2019/11/05/i-fixed-me-o-o/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kevinpan.me/blog/2019/11/05/i-fixed-me-o-o/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Weekend Project: Building A Reddit-Style Commenting System</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I was building &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smashvods.tv&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SmashVODs.tv&lt;/a&gt;, I thought it would be a great idea to add commenting to clips and tournament VODs. What’s a great commenting system? I really enjoy Reddit’s nested comments. So I set out to build it for SmashVODs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the requirements for a Reddit-style commenting system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recursive parent-child comment relationship and terminal condition for scalability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Comment upvotes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Efficient comment fetching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UI to upvote a comment / post a root comment / post a nested comment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UI to show a single comment thread (i.e. render a comment as if it’s the root comment) / navigate up the comment tree&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/78Z4F3Y.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out to implement this system with these requirements without knowing how long it’d take. With a lot of thinking, mashing at the keyboard, and anti-social juice, I managed to build out a fully functioning system in one weekend. You can play around with it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smashvods.tv/matches/604&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;recursive-parent-child-comment-relationship-and-terminal-condition-for-scalability&quot;&gt;1. Recursive parent-child comment relationship and terminal condition for scalability&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was easy to use a relational database (I used Postgres) and Ruby on Rails’s ORM to implement the recursive parent-child comment relationship. Every user had comments, a comment had a reference id to a parent comment. This reference id was nil if it’s a root comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent some time thinking about the terminal condition for the recursion. Should it be infinitely nestable? Should I stop the recursion after a set number of nests? Infinite nestability is cool but there are difficult comment fetching and UI edge cases when the nesting gets extreme that I didn’t want to design and implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up settling with a maximum of 5 nested comments per root comment thread. This felt like a sufficient amount of allowance for nesting that it wouldn’t be a bad user experience, while minimizing the technical effort to implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;comment-upvotes&quot;&gt;2. Comment upvotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was straightforward to implement. Upvotes belonged to a user and a comment. The rest is setting up APIs, data plumbing, and UI design and implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;efficient-comment-fetching&quot;&gt;3. Efficient comment fetching&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the most time thinking about how to implement efficient comment fetching. Ideally, you’d want to show the most popular comments first, not return too many comments, and allow the user to show more comments if there are more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With linear data sets, pagination works really well to make sure you don’t return too many comments. With nested comments, this becomes super tricky. I tried to figure out how Reddit handled this. With large comment threads, some nested comments would be truncated with a link like “6 more replies” and this truncation happened across multiple levels. I couldn’t figure out what heuristic Reddit used to determine when to truncate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/ZVUnLx0.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;caption wide-caption&quot;&gt;
    I&#39;m not sure how Reddit chooses when to truncate the number of comments returned and show &quot;X more replies&quot; links.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also spent a long time thinking about how to fetch a comment tree efficiently without recursion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After much deliberation, I realized that I was spending too much time designing the comment fetching logic when it should &lt;strong&gt;start off simple&lt;/strong&gt;. The system was guaranteed to have low usage to start and if I needed to solve scaling when more people are using it, that’s a good problem to have!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up implementing a naive recursive algorithm to fetch all comments for a comment thread. I returned the entire set of comments on page load. This was straightforward to implement and worked really well. To reduce potentially long pageloads, I fetched a page’s comments only after the rest of the page has loaded. The comment section was mostly below the fold and this had minimal effects on user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ui-to-upvote-a-comment--post-a-root-comment--post-a-nested-comment&quot;&gt;4. UI to upvote a comment / post a root comment / post a nested comment&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two difficult problems to solve with implementing a UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is designing the UI. I’m bad at design and mediocre with CSS (I worship on the altar of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;display: flex&lt;/code&gt;). To fast track design, I took heavy inspiration from the design of Reddit’s comment threads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second problem is architecting the frontend such that users can upvote comments, post root comments, and post nested comments without the code resembling an Italian pasta shop. There were many components to reuse, states to handle, and data pathways to set up and this required careful planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/6wu0T3m.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;caption wide-caption&quot;&gt;
    Please no spaghetti!
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I was able to architect something that I was comfortable with, and implement it with minimal debugging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ui-to-show-a-single-comment-thread-ie-render-a-comment-as-if-its-the-root-comment--navigate-up-the-comment-tree&quot;&gt;5. UI to show a single comment thread (i.e. render a comment as if it’s the root comment) / navigate up the comment tree&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be considered a nice-to-have feature but my completionist drive took a hold of me and I wanted to make it possible to expand into comment threads and show nested comments as root comments, similar to how Reddit does it. It turns out, this was mostly a matter of UI design as it only involved a minor tweak to the comment fetching logic in the backend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;bonus-points-soundcloud-style-comments-for-videos&quot;&gt;Bonus points: SoundCloud-style comments for videos&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/nmRkJ6d.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the first weekend building requirements 1-5 and tackled this afterwards. The trickiest aspect of this feature is rendering comment markers in a timeline under the video in a manageable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the requirements for timestamped commments and a video comment timeline:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users can choose to attach a timestamp to a comment based on the video’s current time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Readers can see that a comment has an attached timestamp, and quickly navigate to that point in the video&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Comment markers on the video comment timeline cannot overlap, even if there are many markers in a small location. This constraint should dynamically hold even as users change the size of the browser&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users can quickly display all comments at a particular point in time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Requirement 3 proved to be the hardest to design and implement. I spent hours thinking about the best way to do this such that the edge cases are handled, e.g. if a user increases or decreases the browser’s width.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up deciding to batch comments and partitioning the video timeline into 20 fixed increments. Each batch of comments would thus be part of 4% of the video’s length. If a 4% video segment had more than one comment, I rendered a marker with the comment count on it. A user could view comments in this video segment by clicking on this marker, which causes a special comment view to be displayed such that only root comments within this 4% video segment are shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This solution elegantly solves two key problems. Because the comment markers are batched and shown at predictable non-overlapping points in the timeline, the overlapping comment marker issue is solved. By choosing a 4% increment, I can simply use a 4% CSS width for each comment marker which ensures that comment markers elegantly adjust spacing between each other, even as users change the size of the browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commenting system initially felt daunting to build given all the complex pieces that needed to be combined together. Breaking the problem down into component parts and articulating clear requirements made it easy to manage. The best part about building this is that I can reuse the system across many different side projects which widens the type of website I can build and increases my efficiency in experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 23:06:07 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2019/08/19/building-a-reddit-style-commenting-system-over-a-weekend/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kevinpan.me/blog/2019/08/19/building-a-reddit-style-commenting-system-over-a-weekend/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building AutochessTV.com</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When Riot Games launched Teamfight Tactics, their version of the popular new game genre, “autochess”, I tried it out and was instantly hooked. Autochess games have a simple premise: pick units that the game randomly gives you and place them on a board. Each round, you are pitted against a random opponent in a free-for-all lobby (usually containing 7 other players) where the units on your board fight the opponent’s units. The losing team loses overall player health. If you lose all your health, you’re out. The winner of the game is the last surviving player in the lobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/DUZUKHk.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I get hopelessly addicted to something, I like to turn the addiction into a productive enterprise. For example, when I was addicted to cryptocurrencies during the bull market in 2017, I started a blog to write about everything I was learning about the technology. The blog became popular with readers donating thousands of dollars and companies paying for sponsored articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Teamfight Tactics, I chose to build &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.autochesstv.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AutochessTV.com&lt;/a&gt;. Again, I wanted to funnel my addiction into a productive outlet, but I also wanted to grab business opportunities that present themselves every time a new game becomes popular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;high-level-design&quot;&gt;High level design&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted AutochessTV.com to do one small, but delightful, thing really well. This is the direct application of a learning from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smashvods.tv&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SmashVODs.tv&lt;/a&gt;, a previous website I built for Super Smash Bros Ultimate (SSBU). With SmashVODs.tv, the website tried to do too much in an already crowded space. Given my available free time, maintaining the website became untenable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For AutochessTV.com, I picked the clips feature from SmashVODs.tv and focused AutochessTV.com on just this feature. Essentially, SmashVODs.tv polled and saved popular SSBU clips from Twitch’s API, and presented these clips in an easy to discover and watch format, something that Twitch is not great at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/SaFDZ2e.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-a-great-clips-discovery-and-watch-experience&quot;&gt;What is a great clips discovery and watch experience?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clips is one of Twitch’s best features (I might be biased) where viewers can click one button to create a short clip of the last 30 seconds to 1 minute of a live stream. When something amazing happens on stream, you bet that a legion of viewers will clip the moment and share. As such, Clips is a great system to find the most exciting moments on Twitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitch has never invested in a great discovery and watch experience for clips, which presents opportunities for third party developers. I’ve spent way too much time thinking about what is a great clips discovery and watch experience. In my opinion, here’s what’s needed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch experience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continuous watching: easy to watch multiple clips at once&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Community interaction: reacting, commenting, and saving clips make the experience even more delightful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery experience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brainless: “show me the best trending clips, without redundancy”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chronological discovery: “show me the best clips last month”, “show me the best clips 2 years ago”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sentiment discovery: “show me the funniest clips”, “show me the most exciting clips”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Topical discovery: “show me clips of raid boss Shyvana”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multivariate discovery: “show me the funniest fail clips of DisguisedToast for the last month”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;clips-experience-on-autochesstvcom&quot;&gt;Clips experience on AutochessTV.com&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable a seamless continuous clips watching experience, I chose to go with row-by-row viewing, similar to Reddit’s post browsing experience. To watch the next clip, a user simply needs to click the next row. A couple benefits of this design: no additional page loads and a user can easily understand (spatially) where they are on the site when transitioning between clips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable community interaction, I added a clips saving feature (ported over from SmashVODs.tv) and a reactions bar (also ported over from SmashVODs.tv). To save or react, users need to be signed in. The reactions bar is interesting; to not make the site feel like a ghost town on launch, I built a sentiment analysis system that periodically assigns “fake” reactions to a clip, normalized by view count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/PJ5YcCX.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For clips discovery, I wanted it to be, first and foremost, brainless. To do so, I created the “Top Gameplay” category. This category contains manually curated clips. As my cron job polls the Twitch API for recent popular Teamfight Tactics clips, I personally sift through the noise to find clips with great gameplay. This is fun and easy to do. For anyone that just wants to watch the most recent and best clips, they only need to use the “Top Gameplay” category, which is presented by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/LSOgWNZ.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other ways to discover clips include sorting by recency or popularity for “All Clips” or “Top Gameplay” clips, and users can specify different time periods to return clips from (e.g. last 48 hours, 30 days, or a specific month).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/R1OYggm.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-note-on-sentiment-analysis&quot;&gt;A note on sentiment analysis&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a technical perspective, I find the most interesting aspect of the site is the sentiment analysis for clips. When I set out to build the system, I decided that it needed to have two core requirements: reaction counts match the sentiment of the clip and reaction counts must feel realistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I implement these two requirements with a few heuristics. To determine the sentiment of a clip, I poll the clip’s chat. For each chat message, I extract tokens and match each token with a fixed list of tokens per sentiment. For example, my list of tokens that match the “funny” sentiment include: “LUL”, “OMEGALUL”, “lol”, “haha”, etc. After classifying each token per message, I assign a sentiment to the message. Then, I calculate the overall sentiment of the clip by aggregating and normalizing the sentiments of all messages. It’s important to note that the sentiment I calculate for a clip is multidimensional (e.g. 30% funny, 10% exciting, 0% scary).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I periodically assign fake reactions to the clip based on the sentiment analysis, normalized by the clip’s view count. Using the clip’s view count, I calculate the ideal total reaction count of the clip and the fake reaction assigner uses a logarithmic function to assign fake reactions to the clip. The vertical asymptote of the logarithmic function is the clip’s ideal total reaction count. In assigning fake reactions, I leverage the multidimensional sentiment of the clip and also heuristically introduce some noise to make the reactions feel real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/FvgiRnp.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;growing-autochesstvcom&quot;&gt;Growing AutochessTV.com&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A website with a great user experience with no way to discover it is always worse than a website with a mediocre user experience but great discovery (is Reddit a good example?). My own copypasta website, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitchquotes.com&quot;&gt;TwitchQuotes.com&lt;/a&gt; is successfuly mostly because it ranks highly on a few high traffic Google search queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To grow AutochessTV.com, I’m considering leaning into Google by building one or two features that are ideal for search engine indexing. Embedded Twitch clips is, unfortunately, not great for search engine indexing. One feature could be a forum to discuss Teamfight Tactics team compositions. Forum posts are text heavy and Google likes when there’s more text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, my existing audience funnels consist primarily of traffic from Reddit links and TwitchQuotes.com referrals. TwitchQuotes.com has 40k unique visitors a month and I’m advertising AutochessTV.com on TwitchQuotes.com. Reddit traffic can be insane. Successful link shares can result in thousands of visitors a day. This traffic, however, is short term and dies down the moment the link leaves a subreddit’s front page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of website development is fast experimentation and securing that long term top of the funnel traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 02:02:14 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2019/08/19/building-autochesstv-com/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kevinpan.me/blog/2019/08/19/building-autochesstv-com/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hawk Hill</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hawk Hill is a small hill found immediately north of the Golden Gate Bridge. At its peak, it’s 281m above sea level. I’m not much of a bird watcher but according to Wikipedia, the hill is a great lookout point for the “largest known flight of diurnal raptors (bird of preys) in the Pacific states”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hawk Hill is also a very popular cycling destination. Once you cross the Golden Gate Bridge, take the first left which gets you on the road going up the hill. The entire climb consists of 600 feet of elevation spread over 2 miles. The average grade is 5.7% and the maximum grade is 14.2%. At a leisurely pace, the climb should take at most half an hour. In my opinion, it’s not too short nor is it too long and there’s enough steepness that it’s always satisfying reaching the top. The climb is also very scenic. From the foot of the hill all the way up, there are amazing views of San Francisco to the south and the Pacific Ocean to the west. Of course, the views are even better when you’re cruising down the hill at 30 miles per hour on the way back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hawk Hill is definitely one of my favorite bike rides in San Francisco. Since the hill is super close to the city, it’s not a big commitment to go on the ride and I’ve climbed it many many times since my first internship in the city last year. Here’s a photo compilation of a few of these climbs…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sunrise-at-battery-spencer&quot;&gt;Sunrise at Battery Spencer&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I went up the hill I didn’t climb to the top. Instead, I stopped at Battery Spencer which was only 15% of the way up the hill to catch the sunrise. I was inclined to keep climbing but convinced myself that I should get to work soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/CSBprUT.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hawk-hill-sunrise&quot;&gt;Hawk Hill sunrise&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Battery Spencer ride, I really wanted to go the entire way. I picked another morning before work and hustled my way to the top before the sunrise. Made it just in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/IZRkldS.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hawk-hill-daytime&quot;&gt;Hawk Hill daytime&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you reach the top of Hawk Hill, there are two ways you can bike down. You could go back the way you came from or you could take the steeper western descent. This descent is just as scenic as its eastern counterpart, if not more. As you go down, you can see San Francisco’s western neighbourhoods to your left and the Point Bonita Lighthouse against the backdrop of the Pacific Ocean in front of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/yqwfBRj.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hawk-hill-is-foggy&quot;&gt;Hawk Hill is foggy&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my second internship in the city, I lived by the Presidio which was super close to Hawk Hill. The entire ride from my apartment to the hill and back took only 45 minutes and I’d often go on the ride as a morning workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one such morning the the hill was super foggy. Instead of the usual views of the city and the ocean, it was just a blanket of grey. With the thick wisps of fog hugging the hill sides and not a soul in sight, climbing up felt surreal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the peak, I found my way into one of the abandoned military bunkers found at the top of the hill. The bunker had an open air lookout facing west that, on a clear day, would have expansive views of the Pacific Ocean. Today, it was all grey. No matter, I just wanted somewhere secluded to enjoy the peace and quiet. Occasionally, you could hear the voices of distant tourists carried over by the wind but this just added to the tranquil ambiance. The real world and all its problems felt so far away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/sJhD2C6.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/8cRa0yN.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hawk-hill-during-fleet-week&quot;&gt;Hawk Hill during Fleet Week&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/10/08/sf-fleet-week/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; on watching the 2016 San Francisco Fleet Week. Fleet Week lasts a whole week (surprise, surprise) and the highlight, at least for me, is the extensive airshow performed over the city during the last couple days. Of course, I couldn’t pass up the opportunity to watch the airshow from Hawk Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/iAVKsVh.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hawk-hill-at-night&quot;&gt;Hawk Hill at night&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also went up Hawk Hill one night but didn’t manage to take great photos. It was cold and windy but the novel experience and the view of San Francisco at night made it worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/JJopRmh.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Sep 2017 14:17:56 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2017/09/16/hawk-hill/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kevinpan.me/blog/2017/09/16/hawk-hill/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>CS488 Project: Extended Ray Tracer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m currently taking the course, &lt;em&gt;CS488: Introduction to Computer Graphics&lt;/em&gt;, at the University of Waterloo. The course’s final project is open-ended and you’re expected to create a set of objectives, within reasonable constraints, and implement them into one cohesive graphics program. This post provides a brief overview of the ray tracer I wrote as my final project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray tracing is fundamentally a computer image generation technique where simulated light rays are fired from a virtual camera into a virtual scene. The light rays might intersect with objects in the scene and these intersections determine the final image’s pixel colours. Ray tracing is generally very slow but it can create photorealistic images. This is why it’s often used in film and rarely used in video games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my final project, I had to choose and implement 10 different ray tracer features. I’ve provided a brief description for each of them below, and also included sample renderings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ray tracer is written in C++ and Lua is used as the modelling language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objective-1-cone-and-cylinder-primitives&quot;&gt;Objective 1: Cone and Cylinder primitives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ray tracer is an extension of the ray tracer built in assignment 4. The previous ray tracer supports sphere, cube, and mesh primitives. I’ve added cone and cylinder primitives in this version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/X7ydXcs.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objective-2-reflection-and-refraction&quot;&gt;Objective 2: Reflection and Refraction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflection is implemented by firing secondary reflection rays when light rays hit reflective objects. The new ray’s direction is determined using the law of reflection. Reflection rays can recursively generate more reflection rays if they hit reflective objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refraction is similar to reflection, except that we use Snell’s law instead of the law of reflection to determine the direction of secondary rays. The law takes into account the indices of refraction between the two mediums that the ray is passing through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this ray tracer, refractive objects are also reflective. Fresnel coefficients are used to determine the amount of light that is refracted and reflected at different points on the object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/KRh1U6T.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objective-3-glossy-reflection-and-refraction&quot;&gt;Objective 3: Glossy reflection and refraction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glossiness is implemented by generating multiple secondary reflection/refraction rays per intersection and averaging the results. The direction of each ray is randomly perturbed by an amount proportional to the object’s glossiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of glossy samples taken per ray intersection determines how noisy the glossy effect is. The more samples, the less noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sharpness of the glossy effect can be adjusted using the material’s phong exponent. The larger the phong exponent, the sharper the image. As the phong exponent approaches infinity, glossiness turns into mirror reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/Xhcy5Rr.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;caption wide-caption&quot;&gt;
    Cylinder on the left is refractive and cylinder on the right is glossy refractive and slightly reflective.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/iaL85xC.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;caption wide-caption&quot;&gt;
    Sphere on the left is glossy with 3 samples taken per intersection while the right is glossy with 20 samples taken per intersection. Phong exponent is 20.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/gTdvyvh.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;caption wide-caption&quot;&gt;
    Sphere on the left is glossy with 3 samples taken per intersection while the right is glossy with 20 samples taken per intersection. Phong exponent is 500.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objective-4-texture-mapping&quot;&gt;Objective 4: Texture mapping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Texture mapping is implemented by mapping surface coordinates on an object to texture coordinates. The texture coordinates are then used to query a texture (rectangular image) to determine the object’s colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/FTcO01v.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;caption wide-caption&quot;&gt;
    Earth, demonstrating spherical texture mapping.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/sJHkxJD.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;caption wide-caption&quot;&gt;
    F-15C Eagle fighter aircraft, demonstrating texture mapping for meshes.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/wPIy530.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objective-5-bump-mapping&quot;&gt;Objective 5: Bump mapping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like texture mapping, bump mapping also requires mapping object surface coordinates to texture coordinates. However, instead of using texture colours to colour the object’s surface, we use them to determine how normals on the surface are perturbed. Perturbing surface normals creates different lighting patterns that simulate the appearance of a bumpy surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/uQ9CkiC.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;caption wide-caption&quot;&gt;
    Earth, demonstrating spherical bump mapping.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objective-6-phong-shading&quot;&gt;Objective 6: Phong shading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phong shading is implemented by interpolating vertex normals across a triangle’s surface to create the appearance of a smooth surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/bHhtgNr.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objective-7-soft-shadows&quot;&gt;Objective 7: Soft shadows&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soft shadows are implemented by sending multiple shadow rays to different sections of a spherical area light. The shadow intensity is determined by the number of shadow rays that are blocked over the total number of shadow rays sent. Area lights are partitioned using a uniform grid and a shadow ray is sent to a random location in each cell. This randomness creates local noise and removes an unnatural “banding” effect in the shadow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of shadow ray samples taken determine global noisiness of the soft shadow. The more samples, the less noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;half-images&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/1NqO1K6.png&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption half-caption&quot;&gt;
      Shadow from a point light.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/rpO0kZ7.png&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption half-caption&quot;&gt;
      Soft shadow from a wide area light. Rendered using 9 shadow ray samples per intersection.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;half-images&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/H20Z8nV.png&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption half-caption&quot;&gt;
      Soft shadow from a narrower area light. Rendered using 9 shadow ray samples per intersection.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/YE3LTLC.png&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption half-caption&quot;&gt;
      Soft shadow from the same area light, but rendered using 4 shadow ray samples per intersection. Notice the increased noise on the shadow.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objective-8-adaptive-anti-aliasing&quot;&gt;Objective 8: Adaptive anti-aliasing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-aliasing eliminates “jaggies”, a type of image artifact where straight or smooth lines have a staircase-like appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-aliasing is performed by partitioning a pixel into uniformly sized subpixels and sending rays into the center of each subpixel. The final colour of a pixel is the average of the colours returned by its subpixel rays. The more samples taken per pixel, the smoother the final image looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In adaptive anti-aliasing, not all pixels are anti-aliased. Ideally, only pixels that need it are anti-aliased. My adaptive anti-aliasing implementation uses two passes to generate the image. The first pass is a standard ray trace. The resulting image is fed to an edge detection algorithm and a second pass, this time with anti-aliasing turned on, retraces the detected edge pixels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/ecxjBSi.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;caption wide-caption&quot;&gt;
    Image before anti-aliasing. Notice the jaggies.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/V5vOc4E.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;caption wide-caption&quot;&gt;
    Edge pixels detected through edge detection algorithm.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/3q6dyQN.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;caption wide-caption&quot;&gt;
    Image after anti-aliasing using 9 samples per anti-aliased pixel.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objective-9-bounding-volume-hierarchy-bvh&quot;&gt;Objective 9: Bounding Volume Hierarchy (BVH)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feature optimizes the speed of the ray tracer by eliminating unnecessary intersection checks. The algorithm starts out by bounding all objects in a scene in one Axis Aligned Bolume Box (AABB) and storing this AABB and the objects it contains in a root node. It then splits these objects into three groups based on location. An AABB and a corresponding child node are created for each group. This process is repeated recursively for each child node and stops when a node contains only one object. The resulting data structure is a tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can speed up intersection checking using BVH through the observation that if a ray fails to intersect with a node’s AABB, it will fail to intersect any of the nodes descendent nodes. Because of the tree structure, BVH allows intersection testing of one ray to be run on $x$ number of model objects, where $x$ is logarithmic in the total number of model objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BVH’s performance is highly dependent on the object partitioning algorithm (i.e. tree balancing algorithm) used to create the BVH tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate the performance increase through BVH, I generated scenes with 1000, 20000, and 50000 spheres. I rendered each scene using non-BVH mode and BVH mode and recorded render times. Here are the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Spheres&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;non-BVH&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;BVH&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;0s&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;150s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;4s&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;542s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;13s&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;relaxed-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/PQIaBsX.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objective-10-final-scene&quot;&gt;Objective 10: Final scene&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/qx2lIWN.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-top: 80px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Special thanks goes towards Professor Baranoski for being a great teacher and for entertaining all the questions I had after class and during office hours. I thoroughly enjoyed CS488 and learned a great deal.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 23:55:48 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2017/03/27/cs488-project-extended-ray-tracer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kevinpan.me/blog/2017/03/27/cs488-project-extended-ray-tracer/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>San Francisco Fleet Week 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Fleet Week is an annual United States Navy, Marine Corp, and Coast Guard tradition. For one week of the year, active military ships, usually deployed overseas, return home and dock in various major cities. It serves as both a vacation for the sailors and a celebration of the three branches of the military involved. During this week, several military-esque events take place within the host cities. For one, the public is allowed to board a select few of the visiting ships. Military demonstrations are also a common occurence (such as a ship parade). Arguably the most prominent of the events, and definitely the loudest, are the airshows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/WvCjaAs.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was initially excited for the ships, particularly because there was a chance an aircraft carrier, an actual Nimitz Class aircraft carrier, would be in the San Francisco Bay. No luck this year but it’s interesting that the HMCS Calgary, a Canadian Navy ship, is visiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of an aircraft carrier was too bad but there were still the airshows to look forward to. I used to be a huge aviation enthusiast and would still be if I had any time these days. Some of that passion lingers, though, and I was excited for the airshows. As with recent SF Fleetweek tradition, the US Navy’s Blue Angels were performing and they are the de facto highlight of the shows. I’ve read a great deal about them and being able to watch them live was a younger Kevin’s dream. The other performances in the show were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Breitling Jet Team (largest civilian aerobatic display team based in France, flying Czech L-39 Albatros jets)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Team Oracle’s Sean D. Tucker flying in a prop plane&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A United Airlines Boeing 747&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The RCAF CF-18 demonstration team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Navy Leap Frogs (parachute demonstration team)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An F-22 raptor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Coast Guard MH65C rescue helicopter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Patriots Jet Team (another civilian demonstration team, based in the US, also flying L-39s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The airshow on Saturday started at noon and ended at 4. The Blue Angels were the last to fly at 3. I biked out to Hawk Hill at noon as a quick “morning” exercise and also to watch the show. The usual road up was restricted to downhill traffic, as a safety precaution for Fleet Week, and I had to climb up from the northside on a road I had only suspected of existing before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather was amazing. Clear skies, no fog, and unusually warm temperatures. It was almost a perfect day for an airshow, if not for the uncharacteristically hot midday sun. The Hawk Hill “summit” offers stunning views of San Francisco, the Golden Gate Bridge, and the Pacific coast. It was a good first stop to watch the show from but was also a bit too far. I did get some pretty impressive pictures of the Breitling team’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image-adj-top&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/Fp4USid.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image-adj-bottom&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/iAVKsVh.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geico… Save money… Geico. This was so compelling, I now have Geico insurance for my nonexistent car, home, and boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/9OSvG2D.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to get closer and the next stop was Battery Spencer. Battery Spencer is at a lower point on Hawk Hill. It’s east of the summit and much closer to the bridge and city. There was a whole lot of people here and not a lot of shade. With the midday sun pressing down on me for so long, it was getting a tad bit uncomfortable. I also forgot to bring sunscreen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/RYUG2FK.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stayed here for a bit too long but managed to see an F-22 Raptor for the first time. It’s probably the most advanced military fighter out there and definitely one of the most iconic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next stop was the Golden Gate Bridge. The eastern path had the best view but was also closed to cycling on the weekends. I had to walk the bridge for the first time and was surprised at how long it took. The United Airlines 747 was demonstrating during this time. The massive passenger jet looked a bit odd doing aerobatics (or as much as a lumbering 747 could) amongst sleek military and civilian one/two-seater jets. Nice ad, United Airlines, but I’m still picking the cheapest flight on hipmunk™ (the fastest, easiest way to plan travel)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/R5r2AO0.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last stop was Fort Mason and it was to watch the Blue Angels. Fort Mason is in the city, on the northern end and directly east of the Golden Gate Bridge. It’s much much closer to the airshow. After all, it’s the Blue Angels and I didn’t want to see them as dots in the sky…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit. I’m a casual. I only use a smartphone camera to take pictures. This is partly why I don’t have amazing photos of the Blue Angels. Some of my friends have posted absolutely gorgeous photos of them and mine pale in comparison. Nevertheless, here are some of my best from today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image-adj-top&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/wVHKww8.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image-adj-center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/CBVhjRX.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image-adj-center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/TrkSwdG.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image-adj-bottom&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/wHpmNic.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, one last thing. After the show, I was heading home and down Bay Street comes this massive group of motorcyclists weaving through traffic. It was pretty cool to see such a large congregation of bikers… I mean, you don’t see that everyday right? Then the intersection turned red for Bay Street and everything turned sour. The bikers continued to cross the street en masse and some of them even took the liberty to stop in front of cars trying to inch into the intersection. Oh my, sorry the cars offended you for trying to cross when it’s green! I was one of the many, the unfortunate, to be blocked by these bikers. The intersection lights turned red for our direction, no one was able to make it through the green. The bikers just kept coming like an endless horde of obnoxiously loud beasts. It turned green again for us, and they kept coming. It wasn’t until the third green did the stream of bikers peter out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a yikes o.o&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/zG4hRPj.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2016 23:00:05 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/10/08/sf-fleet-week/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/10/08/sf-fleet-week/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mount Diablo</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mount Diablo is situated deep in the eastern San Francisco Bay Area (or East Bay), North of Pleasanton and East of Walnut Creek. The mountain is part of the Diablo Range, a mountain range that stretches from East Bay all the way down to the Salinas Valley. Much of the mountain, including its peak, is in protected land via the Mount Diablo State Park. A cursory glance of Mount Diablo’s wiki page reveals an interesting fact: the mountain is sacred to many Native American peoples in California and is even regarded by some as the point of creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/zZ2DXlM.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three iconic bike climbs in the Bay Area: Mount Diablo, Mount Tamalpais (Mount Tam), and Mount Hamilton (Mount Ham? No not really). I haven’t attempted the latter two but Mount Diablo is apparently “less tranquil than Mount Hamilton and less scenic than Mount Tam”. At least it has the best name. It’s summit is 3849 feet above sea level and the climb from the south is about 3300 feet. This is spread over 11.3 miles and has an average grade of 5.8%. Not too bad but it definitely warrants extra training before, especially for the inexperienced. The mountain is easily accessible by Bart. The base is only 6 miles from the Walnut Creek station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/M1EUvbe.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This state park entrance is known as the North Gate. What’s weird is that it’s located way south of the park. Past it, the road gets significantly steeper and the real climbing begins. It was going to be an especially hot day and I could definitely feel the heat rising by this time. Thankfully, the humidity stayed low and it was bearable. I neglected to put on sunscreen (not smart) but surprisingly, I didn’t get a sunburn. This has been a consistent phenomenon over many of my previous bike trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/ClLdcmH.jpg?3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mountain and its surroundings looked extremely dry. It was a sea of yellow with the occasional green shrubs and trees. Was this because of the drought or was this seasonally normal? Hopefully the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/Ze6g6CV.jpg?2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was taken at around 2000 feet. The entire climb had so far been a slow grind with the intermittent struggle when the road became exceptionally steep. Thankfully, the steep points were far and few in between. It’s actually a very rewarding process as you can gauge progress by how much the view has improved since the last time you looked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image-adj-top&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/dEi94iE.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image-adj-bottom&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/XBnEPIf.jpg?2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were taken at around 2500 to 3000 feet. Remarkable views but very tired legs. The thought of all the food I could eat at the summit served as a good motivator. Really, who could say no to protein and granola bars? Exquisite! No kidding though, good views and strenous exercise makes even bland food tasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/PWteCnq.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally made it! Fittingly, the last hundred yards was the most brutal of the whole climb. It gets up to 16% grade and you’re pretty much forced to ride standing up. Needless to say, I was quite tired and was highly tempted to walk the last bit. I couldn’t do it. I could see the finish line and pushed on for the summit views (and the food).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summit had a parking lot with a quaint little stone building (the Visitor Center) overlooking the Northern California landscape. Apparently you could actually stand on the very tip of the mountain inside the Visitor Center although I didn’t know it then. The building also had a roof that was open to visitors. The best views can be found there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my pleasant surprise, the summit was a lot less busy than what I would’ve expected for noon on a Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/OH5QVpH.jpg?2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The viewshed at Mount Diablo’s summit is quite impressive. Some even say that it’s the largest in the world (though unfounded). It does indeed have one of the best in the Western United States and this is remarkable considering it’s relatively low elevation. The Sierra Nevada is clearly visible from the summit and apparently you should also be able to see Sentinel Dome in Yosemite and the Golden Gate Bridge in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure I downed over a thousand calories in a far shorter time than socially appropriate at the summit. Some say your appetite actually diminishes after long periods of exercise. Not me, mine balloons. Guilt-free eating is the best kind of eating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food consumed, views admired, all that’s left was the downhill. It’s the easiest part of the trip, physically at least, and also the most dangerous. Although you can’t feel it during the climb, the mountain road twists and turns at sharp angles and a miscalculation in speed when entering any of these turns could have disastrous consequences. This is especially true with the frequent car coming up the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m no pro at cycling and definitely not great at making sharp turns at high speeds. There are some that are, and they do it angled over as you often see motorcyclists do in races. I can’t (yet) and maybe it’s for the better. Each of my corners was preceeded by generous braking. Nonetheless, it was a very scenic downhill and the effortless biking at such high speeds made it even better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, Mount Diablo was a challenging but fun and rewarding ride. After a busy week, I definitely enjoyed having some time to myself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 01:52:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/10/04/mt-diablo/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/10/04/mt-diablo/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Livermore Bike Ride</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This was the last long distance bike trip that I went on during my internship in San Francisco earlier this year. Up till then, my bike trips have mostly involved biking directly from my Financial District apartment and this meant that I wasn’t able to venture too far from the city proper. This trip was different. It was going to be around the eastern outskirts of a small-ish town across the bay called Livermore. Getting there involved taking the Bart to the easternmost terminal station (the Dublin/Pleasanton station) and biking even further eastward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d been inspired to go on this trip by a popular cyclist on Strava. It seemed like I was going to be biking through a baby mountain range with rolling green hills and valleys filled with wind turbines along the way. I would later find out this place was known as the Altamont Pass Wind Farm and it’s one of the earliest wind farms in the United States. I’ve never been to a wind farm before and pictures of the route online offered glimpses of fantastic views. It was hard to say no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;fit-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/Lou5tFE.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The train ride from San Francisco to the Dublin/Pleasanton station took around an hour and I soon found myself biking along wide stretches of open road towards Livermore. The weather was perfect for a long distance bike trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Livermore is known for its vineyards and wineries and although it’s nowhere near as popular as Napa Valley or Sonoma, the town still manages to attract a good deal of out-of-town visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/hV4Z0lV.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Google Maps, I was climbing the moment I left the Bart station but the road is shallow enough, initially, that it’s hardly noticeable that I was biking uphill. I only started to feel the climb after biking several miles eastward when the urban landscape turned rural. It’s not a short climb either and this was going to be one of many during the trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/kMugZ5g.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The climb is steepest near the top and up till this point, you won’t be seeing many wind turbines. I remember I encountered about two or three but that’s it. This changes dramatically as you reach the peak. The view of a steep uphill road from moments before melts away and becomes that of a wide green valley dotted with wind turbines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/LlylggA.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was such a perfect way to end the long climb. The sparse traffic on the road made for a very peaceful experience. It was just me, my bike, and the occasional soft breeze. After a busy week at work, moments like these were very welcoming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/4yyydNC.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downhill following the climb is probably the best I’ve experienced ever. That’s not saying much since I’ve only started biking “seriously” at the start of the term and haven’t been to many places. Nevertheless, ten kilometres of downhill on a straight road with sparse traffic would make any road cyclist happy. My previous experiences with long stretches of downhill were mostly on curvy mountain roads where a car can appear at any time behind a bend in the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s really unfortunate that, at the end of the stretch of downhill road, I got a pretty bad case of hay fever. I shouldn’t be surprised though, as I was probably exposed to a gazillion pollen particles going down. Luckily, I brought some Claritin pills with me as a precaution but they only worked up to a certain degree. I still had to put up with hay fever for the rest of the ride :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/8aAyQBf.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/Rsq0pyh.jpg?1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You encounter a great deal of livestock throughout this route. It sounds mundane but one of the more memorable moments for me was seeing a herd of cows moving along against the backdrop of several large wind turbines lazily turning in the wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/NwTrDHg.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the bike trip was filled with even more uphills and downhills, though none as long and steep as the first. The trip in total had around 2500 feet of climbing but doing so with hay fever makes it feel so much worse. Overall, it was around 90 kilometers of biking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the view I got at the end of the day. Almost as good as the one at the top of the first hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/OlB0uFO.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 19:09:25 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/07/18/in-and-around-livermore/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/07/18/in-and-around-livermore/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on writing a resume</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I attended a resume critique session for lower year Software Engineers. I was able to critique four or five resumes and noticed a few common mistakes people tended to make. I wish I could’ve gone through more but my time is limited and I hope that through writing this blog post, I can reach out and help significantly more people than I ever could going over resumes one at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I solve problems, I often prefer to take a step back and tackle them from first principles. How does this apply to resume-writing? Well the fundamental challenge is to successfully advertise yourself to recruiters… recruiters who are often looking through large piles of resumes trying to find the best candidates to interview. I really want to emphasize this point, it is often the case that recruiters do not have significant time to spend reading your resume given how many others they have to go over. Understand this constraint and create a resume that optimizes for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;highlight-what-makes-you-exceptional&quot;&gt;Highlight what makes you exceptional&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to make a positive impression in a short time frame is to highlight the achievements that distinguish you from the crowd. Highlight them as aggressively as you can within aesthetic and organizational boundaries. These achievements could include programming competition awards, a mobile app getting X amount of downloads, basically anything that you did that someone else most likely couldn’t have done as well. Optimally, they should be able to be seen and understood with one cursory scan of the resume. Consider experimenting with your friends to see how noticeable they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a few resumes last night that had some really impressive achievements listed. For example, this person ranked in the top 2% for some programming competition and had multiple very successful side projects. Unfortunately, these achievements were all near the bottom of the resume and I had to trudge through hefty job descriptions to finally notice them. There were definitely ways to make these achievements more apparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exceptional achievements are what many recruiters like to see and should not be underestimated. If you have them, leverage them as much as you can!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;leadership-over-independence&quot;&gt;LEADERSHIP over INDEPENDENCE&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common trend I noticed last night was that people really liked highlighting that they were the sole developer on a project, that they “independently” built this piece of software. What they’re trying to say here is that they did a lot of work and have the technical capabilities to build something without significant help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are all great things to have, don’t get me wrong, but there is a much better way to phrase things. Recruiters are often looking for developers that are great communicators and team players. Emphasizing independent work does not attest to how great of a team player you might be and almost makes it seem like you worked as a separate entity from your team. Regardless if that’s true or not, you want to show the best of yourself on your resume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead of writing…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Independently built this feature or software…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest writing this…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Lead the development of this feature or software…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leadership is a very positive quality that all companies value highly. It does not rule out working well independently nor does it rule out being a great team player. In fact, it makes it sound as if you’re great at both!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;be-concise-and-easily-understood&quot;&gt;Be concise and easily understood&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the resumes I critiqued last night had many bloated bullet points. These points spanned multiple lines and discussed in great detail the technical aspects of the project. It seemed like the authors were trying to express the fact that they did a lot of work. They decided to do so by cramming as much information into a bullet point as it was stylistically acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is, a recruiter usually has a limited technical background and likely wouldn’t be able to appreciate the technical details of a project. Even for developers, if they were short on time, they are unlikely to put in the effort to read and fully understand the details. Sure they could infer that you must have worked hard from the amount you wrote, but they are left confused as to what you actually built and how important the work was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the best way to approach this is to split the point into two. Use the first point to describe, concisely and at a high level, what your project is about and why it is significant. Use the second point to state directly that you worked hard, that you did a lot of things behind the scenes to make your project a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, instead of saying…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned Node.js and PostgreSQL to build an application that blah blah blah&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Break it into these points…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;margin-bottom: 8px&quot;&gt;Built an application that does this and is important because blah blah blah&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learned Node.js and PostgreSQL for project. Researched and implemented these algorithms to make these features of the application possible etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, your recruiter not only has a good idea about what you worked on, but also doesn’t have to infer that you are hardworking and capable. You took the initiative and expressed confidence by stating it directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-over-how&quot;&gt;WHAT over HOW&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This point is somewhat related to the previous point. Some resumes last night had the tendency to prioritise technical details over what the work was able to accomplish. For example, the technical aspects were either elaborated on first or bolded. As software engineers, we tend to get caught up in the details of the underlying design and the code. This is perfectly reasonable, writing software is not easy and it’s these details that result in technical success. Unfortunately, as mentioned before, it is often the case that the resume screener either does not have a strong technical background or does not have the time to understand these details, especially if it was outside of their domain. You are much better off describing the results of your work and their importance before following up with the technical elements. The reader will have an easier time understanding your work and you will more likely hold their interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also going to go on a whim here and say that people are generally more interested in the results rather than how the results were achieved. Do car commercials ever spend significant time showing off how a car was built or how they were able to achieve that high mileage?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 11:05:37 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/05/11/thoughts-on-writing-a-resume/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kevinpan.me/blog/2016/05/11/thoughts-on-writing-a-resume/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
